<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>life on victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/life/</link><description>Recent content in life on victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 04:00:43 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/life/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Digital resilience: redundancy for websites and communications</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/digital-resilience-redundancy-for-websites-and-communications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 04:00:43 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/digital-resilience-redundancy-for-websites-and-communications/</guid><description>When what seems like half the planet noped out of WhatsApp after its terms of service update, applications like Signal (which I highly recommend) saw an unprecedented increase in user traffic. Signal had so many new users sign up that it overwhelmed their existing infrastructure and lead to a 24-hour-ish outage. The small team responded impressively quickly, especially given that a 4,200% spike in new users was utterly implausible before it ocurred.</description></item><item><title>Make your own independent website</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/make-your-own-independent-website/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 08:41:27 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/make-your-own-independent-website/</guid><description>The web that raised me was a digital playground in the truest sense. It was made up of HTML experiments frankensteined together by people still figuring it all out.
The beauty of not completely knowing what you&amp;rsquo;re doing is a lack of premature judgement. Without a standard to rise to, you&amp;rsquo;re free to go sideways. Explore. Try things that don&amp;rsquo;t work, without any expectation they will work. An open world with a beginner&amp;rsquo;s mindset.</description></item><item><title>How to get hired as a software developer</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-get-hired-as-a-software-developer/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 05:50:53 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-get-hired-as-a-software-developer/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m asked this question a lot, so let me be the first to give you the good news: there&amp;rsquo;s no one right answer. As general tech-literacy increases, the culture of the coding industry is steadily, thankfully, moving away from a checklist approach. Instead of degrees and pre-requisites when it comes to deciding whether you&amp;rsquo;re qualified to be hired as a software developer, companies (including my own) are far more concerned with just one question.</description></item><item><title>How to become a software developer</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-become-a-software-developer/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jan 2021 04:50:07 -0600</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-become-a-software-developer/</guid><description>As a Director of Engineering, I’m a software developer who hires and leads other software developers. It’s not surprising then that I get asked this question a lot, in various forms:
How do I become a software developer? What language or framework should I learn first? Where do I start? While I’m certain there’s no one right answer for everyone, I’m also certain that the world needs more software developers and systems thinkers.</description></item><item><title>So you're the family tech support</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/so-youre-the-family-tech-support/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2020 08:42:24 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/so-youre-the-family-tech-support/</guid><description>🎄🌟 Happy holidays! 🌟🎄
For those of you seeing relatives this season, chances are that you’re the designated family tech support. If part of your time home for the holidays is spent on software updates and troubleshooting WiFi, here are a few other quick wins to help boost your family&amp;rsquo;s online privacy and security.
1. Set up a VPN Using a VPN is Online Safety 101, but the biggest barrier to effectiveness is not remembering to turn it on.</description></item><item><title>Three rules for choosing a VPN that takes your privacy seriously</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-rules-for-choosing-a-vpn-that-takes-your-privacy-seriously/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 04:41:37 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-rules-for-choosing-a-vpn-that-takes-your-privacy-seriously/</guid><description>Most people know that a VPN is meant to protect your privacy on public or open Wi-Fi. A lesser-known purpose is to protect your privacy right in your own home, from your own internet service provider (ISP).
A set of Federal Communications Commission (FCC) rules entitled &amp;ldquo;Protecting the Privacy of Customers of Broadband and Other Telecommunications Services&amp;rdquo; were unfortunately struck down in 2017. These rules would have prevented ISPs from using and selling your sensitive personal data, such as precise geographic location, health and financial information, web browsing history, and even the content of the messages you send.</description></item><item><title>Goals are for Losers</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/goals-are-for-losers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 06:36:36 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/goals-are-for-losers/</guid><description>I needed to grow my skill set, and fast.
I had been working as a freelance software developer. At the time my now-husband and I traveled constantly, living nomadically out of one or two carry-on bags each. All my worldly possessions fit in my 40L backpack. Like a fine wine, I paired this lifestyle with an equally freedom-filled career. I worked on short contracts, hustled for clients, and generally had the time of my life.</description></item><item><title>Look mom, I'm a GitHub Action Hero</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/look-mom-im-a-github-action-hero/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 09:06:33 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/look-mom-im-a-github-action-hero/</guid><description>GitHub recently interviewed me for their blog editorial entitled GitHub Action Hero: Victoria Drake. Here&amp;rsquo;s a behind-the-scenes peek at the original interview questions and my answers.
What is the name of your Action? Please include a link too. Among the several Actions I&amp;rsquo;ve built, I have two current favorites. One is hugo-remote, which lets you continuously deploy a Hugo static site from a private source repository to a public GitHub Pages repository.</description></item><item><title>Technical ergonomics for the efficient developer</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/technical-ergonomics-for-the-efficient-developer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jun 2020 06:33:28 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/technical-ergonomics-for-the-efficient-developer/</guid><description>This article isn&amp;rsquo;t going to tell you about saving your neck with a Roost stand, or your wrists with a split keyboard - I&amp;rsquo;ve already done that. This article is about saving your brain.
When I first began to program full time, I found myself constantly tired from the mental exertion. Programming is hard! Thankfully, you can take some solace in knowing it gets easier with practice, and with a great supporting cast.</description></item><item><title>Outsourcing security with 1Password, Authy, and Privacy.com</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/outsourcing-security-with-1password-authy-and-privacy.com/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 08:12:32 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/outsourcing-security-with-1password-authy-and-privacy.com/</guid><description>We&amp;rsquo;ve already got enough to deal with without worrying about our cybersecurity. When humans are busy and under stress, we tend to get lax in less-obviously-pressing areas, like the integrity of our online accounts. These areas only become an obvious problem when it&amp;rsquo;s too late for prevention.
Cybersecurity can be fiddly and time-consuming. You might need to reset forgotten passwords, transfer multifactor authentication (MFA) codes to different devices, or deal with the fallout of compromised payment details in the event one of your accounts is still breached.</description></item><item><title>Why PixelFed won't save us from Instagram</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/why-pixelfed-wont-save-us-from-instagram/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Feb 2020 19:23:20 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/why-pixelfed-wont-save-us-from-instagram/</guid><description>PixelFed is a decentralized photo sharing network based on the ActivityPub protocol, the same one that Mastodon uses. For a lot of people divorced (or wanting to be) from Instagram over mental health concerns and issues like forced consent to post-GDPR terms, a decentralized social network like PixelFed sounds like an exciting and promising alternative.
Personally, I stopped using Instagram once I accepted the fact that its core premise and integral structure of social interaction was encouraging me to form habits that were harmful to my life goals.</description></item><item><title>The past ten years, or, how to get better at anything</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/the-past-ten-years-or-how-to-get-better-at-anything/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 08:27:31 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/the-past-ten-years-or-how-to-get-better-at-anything/</guid><description>If you want to get better at anything:
Solve your own problems, Write about it, Teach others. 1. Searching, a decade ago I was a young graduate with newly-minted freedoms, and I was about to fall in love. I had plenty of imagination, a couple handfuls of tenacity, and no sense of direction at all.
For much of my youth, when I encountered a problem, I just sort of bumped up against it.</description></item><item><title>Three healthy cybersecurity habits</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-healthy-cybersecurity-habits/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 08:27:31 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-healthy-cybersecurity-habits/</guid><description>In a similar fashion to everyone getting the flu now and again, the risk of catching a cyberattack is a common one. Both a sophisticated social engineering attack or grammatically-lacking email phishing scam can cause real damage. No one who communicates over the Internet is immune.
Like proper hand washing and getting a flu shot, good habits can lower your risk of inadvertently allowing cybergerms to spread. Since the new year is an inspiring time for beginning new habits, I offer a few suggestions for ways to help protect yourself and those around you.</description></item><item><title>The care and feeding of an IoT device</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/the-care-and-feeding-of-an-iot-device/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 08:59:35 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/the-care-and-feeding-of-an-iot-device/</guid><description>Giving someone a puppy for Christmas might work really well in a movie, but in real life often comes hitched to a multitude of responsibilities that the giftee may not be fully prepared to take on. The same is true for Internet of Things (IoT) devices, including Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Alexa-enabled devices, Google Home, and other Internet-connected appliances like cameras, lightbulbs, and toasters. Yes, they have those now.
Like puppies, IoT devices are still young.</description></item><item><title>Personal cybersecurity posture with too many pop culture references</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/personal-cybersecurity-posture-with-too-many-pop-culture-references/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 08:30:12 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/personal-cybersecurity-posture-with-too-many-pop-culture-references/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Zaphod&amp;rsquo;s just this guy, you know?&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ndash; Halfrunt, Hitchhiker&amp;rsquo;s Guide to the Galaxy by Douglas Adams. The book, not the movie. Definitely not the movie.
Some people (🙋🏻‍) are really into cybersecurity, end-to-end encryption, and totally geeked out when they first learned how the Enigma worked. These people are likely to have an innate interest in building a less-than-laughable personal cybersecurity posture.
Most people, unfortunately, consider cybersecurity optional. Most people say things like:</description></item><item><title>On doing great things</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/on-doing-great-things/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 18:36:15 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/on-doing-great-things/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s International Women&amp;rsquo;s Day, and I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about Grace Hopper.
Grace Hopper was an amazing lady who did great things. She envisioned and helped create programming languages that translate English terms into machine code. She persevered in her intention to join the US Navy from the time she was rejected at 34 years old, to being sworn in to the US Navy Reserve three years later, to retiring with the rank of commander at age 60&amp;hellip; then was recalled (twice) and promoted to the rank of captain at the age of 67.</description></item><item><title>How to set up a short feedback loop as a solo coder</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-set-up-a-short-feedback-loop-as-a-solo-coder/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jul 2018 10:08:41 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-set-up-a-short-feedback-loop-as-a-solo-coder/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve spent the last couple years as a solo freelance developer. Comparing this experience to previously working in companies, I&amp;rsquo;ve noticed that those of us who work alone can have fewer iterative opportunities for improvement than developers who work on teams. Integral to having opportunities to improve is the concept of a short feedback loop: a process of incorporating new learning from observation and previous experience continuously over a short period of time.</description></item><item><title>Why I'm automatically deleting my old tweets using AWS Lambda</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/why-im-automatically-deleting-my-old-tweets-using-aws-lambda/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 10:51:15 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/why-im-automatically-deleting-my-old-tweets-using-aws-lambda/</guid><description>From now on, my tweets are ephemeral. Here’s why I’m deleting all my old tweets, and the AWS Lambda function I’m using to do all this for free.
Click here to skip to the code part.
Stuff and opinions I&amp;rsquo;ve only been a one-bag nomad for a little over a year and a half. Before that, I lived as most people do in an apartment or a house. I owned furniture, more clothing than I strictly needed, and enough &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo; to fill at least a few moving boxes.</description></item><item><title>About time</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/about-time/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Nov 2017 14:05:14 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/about-time/</guid><description>This morning I read an article that&amp;rsquo;s been making the rounds lately: Modern Media Is a DoS Attack on Your Free Will.
It&amp;rsquo;s made me think, which I must admit, I at first didn&amp;rsquo;t like. See, when I wake up in the morning (and subsequently wake up my computer) the first thing I do is go on Twitter to catch up on everything I missed while I was asleep. All this before my first coffee, mind you.</description></item><item><title>Things you need to know about becoming a Data Scientist</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/things-you-need-to-know-about-becoming-a-data-scientist/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 13:19:19 +0900</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/things-you-need-to-know-about-becoming-a-data-scientist/</guid><description>I recently attended a panel discussion hosted by General Assembly in Singapore entitled, &amp;ldquo;So you want to be a Data Scientist/Analyst&amp;rdquo;. The panel featured professionals in different stages of their careers and offered a wealth of information to an audience of hopefuls, including tips on how to land a job as a data scientist, and stories debunking myths that color this field.
The panelists Misrab Faizullah-Khan - VP of Data Science, GO_JEK Anthony Ta - Data Scientist, Tech in Asia Leow Guo Jun - Data Scientist, GO_JEK Gabriel Jiang - Data Scientist Adam Drake - Chief Data Officer, Atazzo Here&amp;rsquo;s a rundown of the major points discussed, paraphrased for brevity.</description></item></channel></rss>