<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>algorithms on victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/algorithms/</link><description>Recent content in algorithms on victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 04:02:27 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/algorithms/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>WPA Key, WPA2, WPA3, and WEP Key: Wi-Fi security explained</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/wpa-key-wpa2-wpa3-and-wep-key-wi-fi-security-explained/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 04:02:27 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/wpa-key-wpa2-wpa3-and-wep-key-wi-fi-security-explained/</guid><description>Setting up new Wi-Fi? Picking the type of password you need can seem like an arbitrary choice. After all, WEP, WPA, WPA2, and WPA3 all have mostly the same letters in them. A password is a password, so what&amp;rsquo;s the difference?
About 60 seconds to billions of years, as it turns out.
All Wi-Fi encryption is not created equal. Let&amp;rsquo;s explore what makes these four acronyms so different, and how you can best protect your home and organization Wi-Fi.</description></item><item><title>What is TLS? Transport Layer Security encryption explained in plain english</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/what-is-tls-transport-layer-security-encryption-explained-in-plain-english/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 04:48:39 -0600</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/what-is-tls-transport-layer-security-encryption-explained-in-plain-english/</guid><description>If you want to have a confidential conversation with someone you know, you might meet up in person and find a private place to talk. If you want to send data confidentially over the Internet, you might have a few more considerations to cover.
TLS, or Transport Layer Security, refers to a protocol. &amp;ldquo;Protocol&amp;rdquo; is a word that means, &amp;ldquo;the way we&amp;rsquo;ve agreed to do things around here,&amp;rdquo; more or less.</description></item><item><title>A coffee-break introduction to time complexity of algorithms</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-coffee-break-introduction-to-time-complexity-of-algorithms/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 May 2018 14:08:28 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-coffee-break-introduction-to-time-complexity-of-algorithms/</guid><description>Just like writing your very first for loop, understanding time complexity is an integral milestone to learning how to write efficient complex programs. Think of it as having a superpower that allows you to know exactly what type of program might be the most efficient in a particular situation - before even running a single line of code.
The fundamental concepts of complexity analysis are well worth studying. You&amp;rsquo;ll be able to better understand how the code you&amp;rsquo;re writing will interact with the program&amp;rsquo;s input, and as a result, you&amp;rsquo;ll spend a lot less wasted time writing slow and problematic code.</description></item><item><title>Knapsack problem algorithms for my real-life carry-on knapsack</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/knapsack-problem-algorithms-for-my-real-life-carry-on-knapsack/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 21:00:35 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/knapsack-problem-algorithms-for-my-real-life-carry-on-knapsack/</guid><description>The knapsack problem I&amp;rsquo;m a nomad and live out of one carry-on bag. This means that the total weight of all my worldly possessions must fall under airline cabin baggage weight limits - usually 10kg. On some smaller airlines, however, this weight limit drops to 7kg. Occasionally, I have to decide not to bring something with me to adjust to the smaller weight limit.
As a practical exercise, deciding what to leave behind (or get rid of altogether) entails laying out all my things and choosing which ones to keep.</description></item><item><title>A Unicode substitution cipher algorithm</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-unicode-substitution-cipher-algorithm/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 20:00:28 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-unicode-substitution-cipher-algorithm/</guid><description>Full transparency: I occasionally waste time messing around on Twitter. (Gasp! Shock!) One of the ways I waste time messing around on Twitter is by writing my name in my profile with different Unicode character &amp;ldquo;fonts,&amp;rdquo; 𝖑𝖎𝖐𝖊 𝖙𝖍𝖎𝖘 𝖔𝖓𝖊. I previously did this by searching for different Unicode characters on Google, then one-by-one copying and pasting them into the &amp;ldquo;Name&amp;rdquo; field on my Twitter profile. Since this method of wasting time was a bit of a time waster, I decided (in true programmer fashion) to write a tool that would help me save some time while wasting it.</description></item><item><title>How to code a satellite algorithm and cook paella from scratch</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-code-a-satellite-algorithm-and-cook-paella-from-scratch/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 16:50:24 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-code-a-satellite-algorithm-and-cook-paella-from-scratch/</guid><description>What if I told you that by the end of this article, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to calculate the orbital period of satellites around Earth using their average altitudes and&amp;hellip; You tuned out already, didn&amp;rsquo;t you?
Okay, how about this: I&amp;rsquo;m going to teach you how to make paella!
And you&amp;rsquo;ll have written a function that does the stuff I mentioned above, just like I did for a freeCodeCamp challenge.
I promise there&amp;rsquo;s an overarching moral lesson that will benefit you every day for the rest of your life.</description></item></channel></rss>