<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>privacy on victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/privacy/</link><description>Recent content in privacy on victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 04:00:43 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Digital resilience: redundancy for websites and communications</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/digital-resilience-redundancy-for-websites-and-communications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 04:00:43 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/digital-resilience-redundancy-for-websites-and-communications/</guid><description>When what seems like half the planet noped out of WhatsApp after its terms of service update, applications like Signal (which I highly recommend) saw an unprecedented increase in user traffic. Signal had so many new users sign up that it overwhelmed their existing infrastructure and lead to a 24-hour-ish outage. The small team responded impressively quickly, especially given that a 4,200% spike in new users was utterly implausible before it ocurred.</description></item><item><title>Create a self-hosted chat service with your own Matrix server</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/create-a-self-hosted-chat-service-with-your-own-matrix-server/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 01:38:07 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/create-a-self-hosted-chat-service-with-your-own-matrix-server/</guid><description>Matrix is an open standard for decentralized real-time communication. The specification is production-ready and bridges to tons of silo products like Slack, Gitter, Telegram, Discord, and even Facebook Messenger. This lets you use Matrix to link together disjoint communities in one place, or create an alternative communication method that works with, but is independent of, communication silos.
You can create your own self-hosted Matrix chat for as little as $3.50 USD per month on an AWS Lightsail instance.</description></item><item><title>So you're the family tech support</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/so-youre-the-family-tech-support/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Dec 2020 08:42:24 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/so-youre-the-family-tech-support/</guid><description>🎄🌟 Happy holidays! 🌟🎄
For those of you seeing relatives this season, chances are that you’re the designated family tech support. If part of your time home for the holidays is spent on software updates and troubleshooting WiFi, here are a few other quick wins to help boost your family&amp;rsquo;s online privacy and security.
1. Set up a VPN Using a VPN is Online Safety 101, but the biggest barrier to effectiveness is not remembering to turn it on.</description></item><item><title>Three rules for choosing a VPN that takes your privacy seriously</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-rules-for-choosing-a-vpn-that-takes-your-privacy-seriously/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 04:41:37 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-rules-for-choosing-a-vpn-that-takes-your-privacy-seriously/</guid><description>Most people know that a VPN is meant to protect your privacy on public or open Wi-Fi. A lesser-known purpose is to protect your privacy right in your own home, from your own internet service provider (ISP).
A set of Federal Communications Commission (FCC) rules entitled &amp;ldquo;Protecting the Privacy of Customers of Broadband and Other Telecommunications Services&amp;rdquo; were unfortunately struck down in 2017. These rules would have prevented ISPs from using and selling your sensitive personal data, such as precise geographic location, health and financial information, web browsing history, and even the content of the messages you send.</description></item><item><title>Outsourcing security with 1Password, Authy, and Privacy.com</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/outsourcing-security-with-1password-authy-and-privacy.com/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 08:12:32 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/outsourcing-security-with-1password-authy-and-privacy.com/</guid><description>We&amp;rsquo;ve already got enough to deal with without worrying about our cybersecurity. When humans are busy and under stress, we tend to get lax in less-obviously-pressing areas, like the integrity of our online accounts. These areas only become an obvious problem when it&amp;rsquo;s too late for prevention.
Cybersecurity can be fiddly and time-consuming. You might need to reset forgotten passwords, transfer multifactor authentication (MFA) codes to different devices, or deal with the fallout of compromised payment details in the event one of your accounts is still breached.</description></item><item><title>Three healthy cybersecurity habits</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-healthy-cybersecurity-habits/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Dec 2019 08:27:31 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-healthy-cybersecurity-habits/</guid><description>In a similar fashion to everyone getting the flu now and again, the risk of catching a cyberattack is a common one. Both a sophisticated social engineering attack or grammatically-lacking email phishing scam can cause real damage. No one who communicates over the Internet is immune.
Like proper hand washing and getting a flu shot, good habits can lower your risk of inadvertently allowing cybergerms to spread. Since the new year is an inspiring time for beginning new habits, I offer a few suggestions for ways to help protect yourself and those around you.</description></item><item><title>The care and feeding of an IoT device</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/the-care-and-feeding-of-an-iot-device/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2019 08:59:35 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/the-care-and-feeding-of-an-iot-device/</guid><description>Giving someone a puppy for Christmas might work really well in a movie, but in real life often comes hitched to a multitude of responsibilities that the giftee may not be fully prepared to take on. The same is true for Internet of Things (IoT) devices, including Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Alexa-enabled devices, Google Home, and other Internet-connected appliances like cameras, lightbulbs, and toasters. Yes, they have those now.
Like puppies, IoT devices are still young.</description></item><item><title>Hackers are Googling your plain text passwords: preventing sensitive data exposure</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/hackers-are-googling-your-plain-text-passwords-preventing-sensitive-data-exposure/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 09:10:11 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/hackers-are-googling-your-plain-text-passwords-preventing-sensitive-data-exposure/</guid><description>Last week, I wrote about the importance of properly handling user input in our websites and applications. I alluded to an overarching security lesson that I hope to make explicit today: the security of our software, application, and customer data is built from the ground up, long before the product goes live.
The OWASP Top 10 is a comprehensive guide to web application security risks. It is relied upon by technology professionals, corporations, and those interested in cybersecurity or information security.</description></item></channel></rss>