<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Linux on Victoria Drake - victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/linux/</link><description>Recent content in Linux on Victoria Drake - victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 09:01:23 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to set up OpenVPN on AWS EC2 and fix DNS leaks on Ubuntu 18.04 LTS</title><link>https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-set-up-openvpn-on-aws-ec2-and-fix-dns-leaks-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 09:01:23 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-set-up-openvpn-on-aws-ec2-and-fix-dns-leaks-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts/</guid><description>A guide for setting up your own private VPN service, and understanding and fixing a DNS leak.</description><content:encoded>
&lt;img src="https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-set-up-openvpn-on-aws-ec2-and-fix-dns-leaks-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts/1-subscribe_hu68a3a904d7b732bc9406197bded259ae_170219_640x0_resize_q75_box.jpg" width="640" height="428"/>
&lt;p&gt;While rolling your own Virtual Private Network (VPN) is far more complicated than choosing a VPN provider from someone&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;best VPN 2019&amp;rdquo; list, the more I learn about why someone should use a VPN at all, the less appealing the latter option becomes. Besides the dangers of trusting a fake VPN app or falling victim to a lookalike URL, even &lt;em&gt;legit&lt;/em&gt; VPN service providers have pressures and motivations that may not be aligned with the privacy you hope to be purchasing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Usually, the point of using a VPN is to gain a layer of privacy by disguising your location. If you aren&amp;rsquo;t currently using one, you can see what the Internet knows about where you are at &lt;a href=&#34;https://dnsleaktest.com/&#34;&gt;the DNS leak test website&lt;/a&gt;. You&amp;rsquo;ll see a big hello, your IP address, and your location. If that&amp;rsquo;s a little unsettling, know that a VPN can help to shield your location and online activities from wandering eyes and opportunistic advertisers. The former might be a too-curious or even malicious public-WiFi-cafe-goer, but the latter, counterintuitively, might be your own household Internet Service Provider (ISP).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a VPN means that the Internet can&amp;rsquo;t easily see your location, and your ISP can&amp;rsquo;t see your unencrypted web traffic (and neither can your curious coffee shop neighbor). Your ISP &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; see the amount of data you&amp;rsquo;re sending, in its encrypted form, and that you&amp;rsquo;re sending it to your VPN server - but that&amp;rsquo;s all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unless you have a &lt;a href=&#34;https://dnsleaktest.com/what-is-a-dns-leak.html&#34;&gt;DNS leak&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are still using your ISP&amp;rsquo;s DNS server, they are still able to see all the URLs the server is resolving for you. So they&amp;rsquo;ll know you asked for &lt;code&gt;lastminutebackwax.com&lt;/code&gt;, although they won&amp;rsquo;t be able to decrypt the data that was exchanged with the site. (Is it just me, or does that seem even worse, somehow?)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting up your own instance and VPN service offers some peace of mind over trusting yet another company to do right with your data. Note that a VPN will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; give you complete online anonymity; there are many other ways your Internet presence can be tracked and your location discovered. However, if properly set up, without DNS leaks, you&amp;rsquo;ll have about as much Internet privacy as can be afforded without using &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tor_(anonymity_network)&#34;&gt;Tor&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;setting-up-our-vpn&#34;&gt;Setting up our VPN&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post will cover how to set up the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/B00MI40CAE/&#34;&gt;OpenVPN Access Server&lt;/a&gt; product on AWS Marketplace, running on an &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/ec2/&#34;&gt;Amazon EC2 instance&lt;/a&gt;. Then, we&amp;rsquo;ll look at how to fix a &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.gnome.org/GNOME/NetworkManager-openvpn/issues/10&#34;&gt;known NetworkManager bug in Ubuntu 18.04 that might cause DNS leaks&lt;/a&gt;. The whole process should take about fifteen minutes, so grab a ☕ and let&amp;rsquo;s do some adulting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: IDs and IP addresses shown for demonstration in this tutorial are invalid.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-launch-the-openvpn-access-server-on-aws-marketplace&#34;&gt;1. Launch the OpenVPN Access Server on AWS Marketplace&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/B00MI40CAE&#34;&gt;OpenVPN Access Server&lt;/a&gt; is available on AWS Marketplace. The Bring Your Own License (BYOL) model doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually require a license for up to two connected devices; to connect more clients, you can get &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/seller-profile/ref=srh_res_product_vendor?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;id=aac3a8a3-2823-483c-b5aa-60022894b89d&#34;&gt;bundled billing&lt;/a&gt; for five, ten, or twenty-five clients, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://openvpn.net/pricing/&#34;&gt;purchase a minimum of ten OpenVPN licenses a la carte&lt;/a&gt; for $15/device/year. For most of us, the two free connected devices will suffice; and if using an EC2 Micro instance, our set up will be &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/free/&#34;&gt;AWS Free Tier eligible&lt;/a&gt; as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start by clicking &amp;ldquo;Continue to Subscribe&amp;rdquo; for the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/marketplace/pp/B00MI40CAE&#34;&gt;OpenVPN Access Server&lt;/a&gt;, which will bring you to a page that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;1-subscribe.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Subscription details page for OpenVPN Access Server&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &amp;ldquo;Continue to Configuration.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;2-configure.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Configure this software page for OpenVPN Access Server&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may notice that the EC2 instance type in the right side bar (and consequently, the Monthly Estimate) isn&amp;rsquo;t the one we want - that&amp;rsquo;s okay, we can change it soon. Just ensure that the &amp;ldquo;Region&amp;rdquo; chosen is where we want the instance to be located. Generally, the closer it is to the physical location of your client (your laptop, in this case), the faster your VPN will be. Click &amp;ldquo;Continue to Launch.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;3-launch.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Launch this software page&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this page, we&amp;rsquo;ll change three things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-the-ec2-instance-type&#34;&gt;1. The EC2 Instance type&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Different types of EC2 (Elastic Compute Cloud) instances will offer us different levels of computing power. If you plan to use your instance for something more than just this VPN, you may want to choose something with higher memory or storage capacity, depending on how you plan to use it. We can view each instance offering on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://aws.amazon.com/ec2/instance-types/&#34;&gt;Amazon EC2 Instance Types page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For simple VPN use, the &lt;code&gt;t2.nano&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;t2.micro&lt;/code&gt; instances are likely sufficient. Only the Micro instance is Free Tier eligible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-the-security-group-settings&#34;&gt;2. The Security Group settings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/vpc/latest/userguide/VPC_SecurityGroups.html&#34;&gt;Security Group&lt;/a&gt; is a profile, or collection of settings, that Amazon uses to control access to our instance. If you&amp;rsquo;ve set up other AWS products before, you may already have some groups with their own rules defined. We should be careful to understand the reasons for our Security Group settings, as these define how public or private our instance is, and consequently, who has access to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we click &amp;ldquo;Create New Based on Seller Settings,&amp;rdquo; the OpenVPN server defines some recommended settings for a default Security Group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;4-security-group.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Security group settings&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The default recommended settings are all &lt;code&gt;0.0.0.0/0&lt;/code&gt; for TCP ports 22, 943, 443, and 945, and UDP port 1194. OpenVPN offers an &lt;a href=&#34;https://openvpn.net/vpn-server-resources/amazon-web-services-ec2-byol-appliance-quick-start-guide/#Instance_Launch_Options&#34;&gt;explanation of how the ports are used&lt;/a&gt; on their website. With the default settings, all these ports are left open to support various features of the OpenVPN server. We may wish to restrict access to these ports to a specific IP address or block of addresses (like that of your own ISP) to increase the security of our instance. However, if your IP address frequently changes (like when you travel and connect to a different WiFi network), restricting the ports may not be as helpful as we hope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, our instance will require SSH keys to connect to, and the OpenVPN server will be password protected. Unless you have other specific security goals, it&amp;rsquo;s fine to accept the default settings for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s give the Security Group a name and brief description, so we know what it&amp;rsquo;s for. Then click &amp;ldquo;Save.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;3-the-key-pair-settings&#34;&gt;3. The Key Pair settings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aforementioned SSH keys are access credentials that we&amp;rsquo;ll use to connect to our instance. We can &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSEC2/latest/UserGuide/ec2-key-pairs.html#having-ec2-create-your-key-pair&#34;&gt;create a key pair&lt;/a&gt; in this section, or you can choose a key pair you may already be using with AWS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;5-keys.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Key Pair Settings link&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create a new set of access credentials, click &amp;ldquo;Create a key pair in EC2&amp;rdquo; to open a new window. Then, click the &amp;ldquo;Create Key Pair&amp;rdquo; blue button. Once you give your key pair a name, it will be created and the private key will automatically download to your machine. It&amp;rsquo;s a file ending with the extension &lt;code&gt;.pem&lt;/code&gt;. Store this key in a secure place on your computer. We&amp;rsquo;ll need to refer to it when we connect to our new EC2 instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can return to the previous window to select the key pair we just created. If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t show up, hit the little &amp;ldquo;refresh&amp;rdquo; icon next to the drop-down. Once it&amp;rsquo;s selected, hit the shiny yellow &amp;ldquo;Launch&amp;rdquo; button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should see a message like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;6-launched.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Launch success message&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great stuff! Now that our instance exists, let&amp;rsquo;s make sure we can access it and start up our VPN. For a shortcut to the next step, click on the &amp;ldquo;EC2 Console&amp;rdquo; link in the success message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-associate-an-elastic-ip&#34;&gt;2. Associate an Elastic IP&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.aws.amazon.com/AWSEC2/latest/UserGuide/elastic-ip-addresses-eip.html&#34;&gt;Elastic IP Addresses&lt;/a&gt; provides us with a public IPv4 address controlled by our account, unlike the public IP address tied to our EC2 instance. It&amp;rsquo;s considered a best practice to create one and associate it with our VPN instance. If anything should go wrong with our instance, or if we want to use a new instance for our VPN in the future, the Elastic IP can be dissassociated from the current instance and reassociated with our new one. This makes the transition seamless for our connected clients. Think of the Elastic IP like a web domain address that we register - we can point it at whatever we choose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can create a new Elastic IP address on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://console.aws.amazon.com/ec2/&#34;&gt;Amazon EC2 Console&lt;/a&gt;. If you clicked the link from the success message above, we&amp;rsquo;re already there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;7-ec2.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;EC2 console&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have more than one instance, take note of the Instance ID of the one we&amp;rsquo;ve just launched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the left sidebar under &amp;ldquo;Network &amp;amp; Security,&amp;rdquo; choose &amp;ldquo;Elastic IPs.&amp;rdquo; Then click the blue &amp;ldquo;Allocate new address&amp;rdquo; button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;8-elasticip.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Allocate new address page&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choose &amp;ldquo;Amazon Pool,&amp;rdquo; then click &amp;ldquo;Allocate.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;9-elasticip.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Allocate elastic IP success message&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Success! We can click &amp;ldquo;Close&amp;rdquo; to return to the Elastic IP console.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;10-associateip.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Associate elastic IP&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that we have an Elastic IP, let&amp;rsquo;s associate it with our instance. Select the IP address, then click &amp;ldquo;Actions,&amp;rdquo; and choose &amp;ldquo;Associate address.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;11-associateip.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Associate elastic IP with instance&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ensure the &amp;ldquo;Instance&amp;rdquo; option is selected, then click the drop-down menu. We should see our EC2 instance ID there. Select it, then click &amp;ldquo;Associate.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;12-associateip.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Associate elastic IP success message&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Success! Now that we&amp;rsquo;ll be able to access our VPN instance, let&amp;rsquo;s get our VPN service up and running.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-initialize-openvpn-on-the-ec2-server&#34;&gt;3. Initialize OpenVPN on the EC2 server&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we&amp;rsquo;ll need to connect to the EC2 instance via our terminal. We&amp;rsquo;ll use the private key we created earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Open a new terminal window and navigate to the directory containing the private key &lt;code&gt;.pem&lt;/code&gt; file. We&amp;rsquo;ll need to set its permissions with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;sudo chmod &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;400&lt;/span&gt; &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;.pem&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be sure to substitute &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; with the name of your key.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sets the file permissions to &lt;code&gt;-r--------&lt;/code&gt; so that it can only be read by the user (you). It may help to protect the private key from read and write operations by other users, but more pertinently, will prevent AWS from throwing an error when we try to connect to our instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can now do just that by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;ssh -i &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;.pem openvpnas@&amp;lt;elastic ip&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The user &lt;code&gt;openvpnas&lt;/code&gt; is set up by the OpenVPN Access Server to allow us to connect to our instance. Replace &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;elastic ip&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; with the Elastic IP address we just associated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We may get a message saying that the authenticity of our host can&amp;rsquo;t be established. As long as we&amp;rsquo;ve typed the Elastic IP correctly, we can go ahead and answer &amp;ldquo;yes&amp;rdquo; to the prompt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upon the initial connection to the OpenVPN instance, a set up wizard called &amp;ldquo;Initial Configuration Tool&amp;rdquo; should automatically run. (If, for some reason, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t, or you panic-mashed a button, we can restart it with &lt;code&gt;sudo ovpn-init –ec2&lt;/code&gt;.) We&amp;rsquo;ll be asked to accept the agreement, then the wizard will help to walk us through some configuration settings for our VPN server.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may generally accept the default settings, however, there are a couple questions you may like to answer knowledgeably. They are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Should client traffic be routed by default through the VPN?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why you might like to answer &amp;ldquo;yes&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/em&gt; Answering &amp;ldquo;yes&amp;rdquo; to this option can prevent &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Split_tunneling&#34;&gt;split tunneling&lt;/a&gt;, a situation in which you may bypass the VPN when connected to WiFi networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Should client DNS traffic be routed by default through the VPN?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Why you might like to answer &amp;ldquo;yes&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/em&gt; This setting can help prevent DNS leaks by specifying that DNS requests should be handled by the VPN. If you answer &amp;ldquo;yes&amp;rdquo; to the previous question, it will be enabled regardless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When asked for our &amp;ldquo;OpenVPN-AS license key&amp;rdquo;, we can leave it blank to use the VPN with up to two clients. If you&amp;rsquo;ve purchased a key, enter it here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once the configuration wizard finishes running, we should see the message &amp;ldquo;Initial Configuration Complete!&amp;rdquo; Before we move on, we should set a password for our server&amp;rsquo;s administration account. To do this, run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;sudo passwd openvpn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then enter your chosen password twice. Now we&amp;rsquo;re ready to get connected!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To close the ssh connection, type &lt;code&gt;exit&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-connect-the-client-to-the-vpn&#34;&gt;4. Connect the client to the VPN&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To connect our client (in this case, our laptop) to the VPN and start reaping the benefits, we&amp;rsquo;ll need to do two things; first, obtain our connection profile; second, install the &lt;code&gt;openvpn&lt;/code&gt; daemon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;1-get-your-ovpn-connection-profile&#34;&gt;1. Get your &lt;code&gt;.ovpn&lt;/code&gt; connection profile&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll need to download a connection profile for ourselves; this is like a personal configuration file with information, including keys, that the VPN server will need to allow our connection. We can do this by logging in with the password we just set at our Elastic IP address, port 943. This looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;https://&amp;lt;elastic ip&amp;gt;:943/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;https&lt;/code&gt; part is important; without it, the instance won&amp;rsquo;t send any data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we go to this URL, we may see a page warning us that this site&amp;rsquo;s certificate issuer is unknown or invalid. As long as we&amp;rsquo;ve typed our Elastic IP correctly, it&amp;rsquo;s safe to proceed. If you&amp;rsquo;re using Firefox, click &amp;ldquo;Advanced,&amp;rdquo; and then &amp;ldquo;Accept the Risk and Continue.&amp;rdquo; In Chrome, click &amp;ldquo;Advanced,&amp;rdquo; then &amp;ldquo;Proceed to &amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; the elastic IP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;13-warning.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Security warning page&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Log in with the username &lt;code&gt;openvpn&lt;/code&gt; and the password we just set. We&amp;rsquo;ll now be presented with a link to download our user-locked connection profile:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;14-profile.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Connection profile download page&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we click the link, a file named &lt;code&gt;client.ovpn&lt;/code&gt; will download.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;2-install-and-start-openvpn-on-your-ubuntu-18-04-client&#34;&gt;2. Install and start &lt;code&gt;openvpn&lt;/code&gt; on your Ubuntu 18.04 client&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;openvpn&lt;/code&gt; daemon will allow our client to connect to our VPN server. It can be installed through the default Ubuntu repositories. Run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt install openvpn
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order for OpenVPN to automatically start when we boot up our computer, we&amp;rsquo;ll need to rename and move the connection profile file. I suggest using a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symbolic_link&#34;&gt;symlink&lt;/a&gt; to accomplish this, as it leaves our original file more easily accessible for editing, and allows us to store it in any directory we choose. We can create a symlink by running this command in the directory where our file is located:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;sudo ln -s client.ovpn /etc/openvpn/&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;.conf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This creates a symbolic link for the connection profile in the appropriate folder for &lt;code&gt;systemd&lt;/code&gt; to find it. The &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; can be anything. When the Linux kernel has booted, &lt;code&gt;systemd&lt;/code&gt; is used to initialize the services and daemons that the user has set up to run; one of these will now be OpenVPN. Renaming the file with the extension &lt;code&gt;.conf&lt;/code&gt; will let the &lt;code&gt;openvpn&lt;/code&gt; daemon know to use it as our connection file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For now, we can manually start and connect to OpenVPN by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;sudo openvpn --config client.ovpn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll be asked for a username and password, which will be the same credentials we used before. Once the service finishes starting up, we&amp;rsquo;ll see &amp;ldquo;Initialization Sequence Complete.&amp;rdquo; If we now visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dnsleaktest.com/&#34;&gt;the DNS leak test website&lt;/a&gt;, we should see the Elastic IP and the location of our EC2 server. Yay!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re on a later version of Ubuntu, you may check for DNS leaks by clicking on one of the &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; buttons. If all the ISPs shown are Amazon and none are your own service provider&amp;rsquo;s, congratulations! No leaks! You can move on to &lt;a href=&#34;#3-set-up-openvpn-as-networkmanager-system-connection&#34;&gt;Step 3 in the second section&lt;/a&gt; below, after which, you&amp;rsquo;ll be finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re using Ubuntu 18.04 LTS, however, we&amp;rsquo;re not yet done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;what-a-dns-leak-looks-like&#34;&gt;What a DNS leak looks like&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To see what a DNS leak looks like, click on one of the &amp;ldquo;test&amp;rdquo; buttons on the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dnsleaktest.com/&#34;&gt;the DNS leak test page&lt;/a&gt;. When we do, we&amp;rsquo;ll see not only our Amazon.com IP addresses, but also our own ISP and location.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also see the leak by running &lt;code&gt;systemd-resolve --status&lt;/code&gt; in our terminal. Our results will contain two lines under different interfaces that both have entries for DNS Servers. It&amp;rsquo;ll look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;Link &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;7&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;tun0&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
Current Scopes: DNS
LLMNR setting: yes
MulticastDNS setting: no
DNSSEC setting: no
DNSSEC supported: no
DNS Servers: &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;172&lt;/span&gt;.31.0.2
DNS Domain: ~.
Link &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;wlp4s0&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
Current Scopes: none
LLMNR setting: yes
MulticastDNS setting: no
DNSSEC setting: no
DNSSEC supported: no
DNS Servers: &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;192&lt;/span&gt;.168.0.1
DNS Domain: ~.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/434916/how-to-fix-openvpn-dns-leak&#34;&gt;DNS leak problem in Ubuntu 18.04&lt;/a&gt; stems from Ubuntu&amp;rsquo;s DNS resolver, &lt;code&gt;systemd-resolved&lt;/code&gt;, failing to properly handle our OpenVPN configuration. In order to try and be a good, efficient DNS resolver, &lt;code&gt;systemd-resolved&lt;/code&gt; will send DNS lookup requests in parallel to each interface that has a DNS server configuration, and then utilizes the fastest response. In our case, we only want to use our VPN&amp;rsquo;s DNS servers. Sorry, &lt;code&gt;systemd-resolved&lt;/code&gt;. You tried.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;how-to-fix-openvpn-dns-leak-on-ubuntu-18-04&#34;&gt;How to fix OpenVPN DNS leak on Ubuntu 18.04&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luckily, there is a fix that we can implement. We&amp;rsquo;ll need to install a few helpers from the Ubuntu repositories, update our configuration file, then set up OpenVPN using NetworkManager. Let&amp;rsquo;s do it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;1-install-some-helpers&#34;&gt;1. Install some helpers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To properly integrate OpenVPN with &lt;code&gt;systemd-resolved&lt;/code&gt;, we&amp;rsquo;ll need a bit more help. In a terminal, run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;sudo apt install -y openvpn-systemd-resolved network-manager-openvpn network-manager-openvpn-gnome
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will install a helper script that integrates OpenVPN and &lt;code&gt;systemd-resolved&lt;/code&gt;, a NetworkManager plugin for OpenVPN, and its GUI counterpart for GNOME desktop environment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;2-add-dns-implementation-to-your-connection-profile&#34;&gt;2. Add DNS implementation to your connection profile&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll need to edit the connection profile file we downloaded earlier. Since it&amp;rsquo;s symbolically linked, we can accomplish this by changing the &lt;code&gt;.ovpn&lt;/code&gt; file, wherever it&amp;rsquo;s stored. Run &lt;code&gt;vim &amp;lt;name&amp;gt;.ovpn&lt;/code&gt; to open it in Vim, then add the following lines at the bottom. Explanation in the comments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Allow OpenVPN to call user-defined scripts&lt;/span&gt;
script-security &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Tell systemd-resolved to send all DNS queries over the VPN&lt;/span&gt;
dhcp-option DOMAIN-ROUTE .
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Use the update-systemd-resolved script when TUN/TAP device is opened,&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# and also run the script on restarts and before the TUN/TAP device is closed&lt;/span&gt;
up /etc/openvpn/update-systemd-resolved
up-restart
down /etc/openvpn/update-systemd-resolved
down-pre&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the full list of OpenVPN options, see &lt;a href=&#34;https://openvpn.net/community-resources/reference-manual-for-openvpn-2-1/&#34;&gt;OpenVPN Scripting and Environment Variables&lt;/a&gt;. You may also like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/TUN/TAP&#34;&gt;more information about TUN/TAP&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;3-set-up-openvpn-as-networkmanager-system-connection&#34;&gt;3. Set up OpenVPN as NetworkManager system connection&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll use the GUI to set up our VPN with NetworkManager. Open up Network Settings, which should look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;15-networksettings.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Network Settings window on Ubuntu 18.04&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then click the &amp;ldquo;+&amp;rdquo; button. On the window that pops up, counterintuitively, choose &amp;ldquo;Import from file&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; instead of the OpenVPN option.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;16-importvpn.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Add VPN window&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Navigate to, and then select, your &lt;code&gt;.ovpn&lt;/code&gt; file. We should now see something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;17-vpnsettings.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;The filled VPN connection settings&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add your username and password for the server (&lt;code&gt;openvpn&lt;/code&gt; and the password we set in &lt;a href=&#34;#3-initialize-openvpn-on-the-ec2-server&#34;&gt;the first section&amp;rsquo;s Step 3&lt;/a&gt;), and your user key password (the same one again, if you&amp;rsquo;ve followed this tutorial), then click the &amp;ldquo;Add&amp;rdquo; button.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;4-edit-your-openvpn-networkmanager-configuration&#34;&gt;4. Edit your OpenVPN NetworkManager configuration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly there! Now that we&amp;rsquo;ve added the VPN as a NetworkManager connection, we&amp;rsquo;ll need to make a quick change to it. We can see a list of NetworkManager connections by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;ls -la /etc/NetworkManager/system-connections/*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one for our VPN is probably called &lt;code&gt;openvpn&lt;/code&gt;, so let&amp;rsquo;s edit it by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;sudo vim /etc/NetworkManager/system-connections/openvpn&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under &lt;code&gt;[ipv4]&lt;/code&gt;, we&amp;rsquo;ll need to add the line &lt;code&gt;dns-priority=-42&lt;/code&gt;. It should end up looking like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;18-connsettings.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Connection settings for ipv4&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting a negative number is a workaround that prioritizes this DNS server. The actual number is arbitrary (&lt;code&gt;-1&lt;/code&gt; should also work) but I like 42. ¯\_(ツ)_/¯&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;5-restart-connect-profit&#34;&gt;5. Restart, connect, profit!!!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a terminal, run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-sh&#34; data-lang=&#34;sh&#34;&gt;sudo service network-manager restart&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then in the Network Settings, click the magic button that turns on the VPN:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;19-vpnon.jpg#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Network Settings window&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, visit &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.dnsleaktest.com/&#34;&gt;the DNS leak test website&lt;/a&gt; and click on &amp;ldquo;Extended test&amp;rdquo; to verify the fix. If everything&amp;rsquo;s working properly, we should now see a list containing only our VPN ISP.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;20-noleaks.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Successful DNS leak test results&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we&amp;rsquo;re done! Congratulations on rolling your very own VPN server and stopping DNS leaks with OpenVPN. Enjoy surfing in (relative) privacy. Now your only worry at the local coffeeshop is who&amp;rsquo;s watching you surf from the seat behind you.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><enclosure url="https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-set-up-openvpn-on-aws-ec2-and-fix-dns-leaks-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts/1-subscribe_hu68a3a904d7b732bc9406197bded259ae_170219_640x0_resize_q75_box.jpg" type="image/jpg"/></item><item><title>How to do twice as much with half the keystrokes using `.bashrc`</title><link>https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-do-twice-as-much-with-half-the-keystrokes-using-.bashrc/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 09:17:02 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-do-twice-as-much-with-half-the-keystrokes-using-.bashrc/</guid><description>An overview of time-saving aliases, functions, and creating a useful Bash prompt.</description><content:encoded>
&lt;img src="https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-do-twice-as-much-with-half-the-keystrokes-using-.bashrc/cover_huc91640f9694e31ff03eab28f9c840023_19597_640x0_resize_box_2.png" width="640" height="245"/>
&lt;p&gt;In my &lt;a href=&#34;https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-set-up-a-fresh-ubuntu-desktop-using-only-dotfiles-and-bash-scripts/&#34;&gt;recent post about setting up Ubuntu with Bash scripts&lt;/a&gt;, I briefly alluded to the magic of &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;. This didn&amp;rsquo;t really do it justice, so here&amp;rsquo;s a quick post that offers a bit more detail about what the Bash configuration file can do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My current configuration hugely improves my workflow, and saves me well over 50% of the keystrokes I would have to employ without it! Let&amp;rsquo;s look at some examples of aliases, functions, and prompt configurations that can improve our workflow by helping us be more efficient with fewer key presses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bash-aliases&#34;&gt;Bash aliases&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A smartly written &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; can save a whole lot of keystrokes. We can take advantage of this in the literal sense by using &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/bash/manual/html_node/Aliases.html&#34;&gt;bash aliases&lt;/a&gt;, or strings that expand to larger commands. For an indicative example, here is a Bash alias for copying files in the terminal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Always copy contents of directories (r)ecursively and explain (v) what was done&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;cp&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;cp -rv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;alias&lt;/code&gt; command defines the string we&amp;rsquo;ll type, followed by what that string will expand to. We can override existing commands like &lt;code&gt;cp&lt;/code&gt; above. On its own, the &lt;code&gt;cp&lt;/code&gt; command will only copy files, not directories, and succeeds silently. With this alias, we need not remember to pass those two flags, nor &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; the location of our copied file to confirm that it&amp;rsquo;s there! Now, just those two key presses (for &lt;code&gt;c&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;d&lt;/code&gt;) will do all of that for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few more &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; aliases for passing flags with common functions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# List contents with colors for file types, (A)lmost all hidden files (without . and ..), in (C)olumns, with class indicators (F)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;ls&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;ls --color=auto -ACF&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# List contents with colors for file types, (a)ll hidden entries (including . and ..), use (l)ong listing format, with class indicators (F)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;ll&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;ls --color=auto -alF&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Explain (v) what was done when moving a file&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;mv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;mv -v&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Create any non-existent (p)arent directories and explain (v) what was done&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;mkdir&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;mkdir -pv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Always try to (c)ontinue getting a partially-downloaded file&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;wget&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;wget -c&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aliases come in handy when we want to avoid typing long commands, too. Here are a few I use when working with Python environments:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;pym&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;python3 manage.py&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;mkenv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;python3 -m venv env&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;startenv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;source env/bin/activate &amp;amp;&amp;amp; which python3&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;alias&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;stopenv&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;deactivate&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For further inspiration on ways Bash aliases can save time, I highly recommend &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/an-introduction-to-useful-bash-aliases-and-functions&#34;&gt;the examples in this article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bash-functions&#34;&gt;Bash functions&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One downside of the aliases above is that they&amp;rsquo;re rather static - they&amp;rsquo;ll always expand to exactly the text declared. For a Bash alias that takes arguments, we&amp;rsquo;ll need to create a function. We can do this like so:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Show contents of the directory after changing to it&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;builtin&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
ls -ACF
&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;rsquo;t begin to tally how many times I&amp;rsquo;ve typed &lt;code&gt;cd&lt;/code&gt; and then &lt;code&gt;ls&lt;/code&gt; immediately after to see the contents of the directory I&amp;rsquo;m now in. With this function set up, it all happens with just those two letters! The function takes the first argument, &lt;code&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;, as the location to change directory to, then prints the contents of that directory in nicely formatted columns with file type indicators. The &lt;code&gt;builtin&lt;/code&gt; part is necessary to get Bash to allow us to override this default command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bash functions are very useful when it comes to downloading or upgrading software, too. I previously spent at least a few minutes every couple weeks downloading the new extended version of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/categories/releases&#34;&gt;static site generator Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, thanks to their excellent shipping frequency. With a function, I only need to pass in the version, and the upgrade happens in a few seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Hugo install or upgrade&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; gethugo &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
wget -q -P tmp/ https://github.com/gohugoio/hugo/releases/download/v&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;/hugo_extended_&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;_Linux-64bit.tar.gz
tar xf tmp/hugo_extended_&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;_Linux-64bit.tar.gz -C tmp/
sudo mv -f tmp/hugo /usr/local/bin/
rm -rf tmp/
hugo version
&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;$@&lt;/code&gt; notation simply takes all the arguments given, replacing its spot in the function. To run the above function and download Hugo version 0.57.2, we use the command &lt;code&gt;gethugo 0.57.2&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve got one for &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org/&#34;&gt;Golang&lt;/a&gt;, too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; getgolang &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
sudo rm -rf /usr/local/go
wget -q -P tmp/ https://dl.google.com/go/go&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;.linux-amd64.tar.gz
sudo tar -C /usr/local -xzf tmp/go&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;.linux-amd64.tar.gz
rm -rf tmp/
go version
&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or how about a function that adds a remote origin URL for GitLab to the current repository?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; glab &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
git remote set-url origin --add git@gitlab.com:&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$@&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;PWD&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;##*/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;.git
git remote -v
&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With &lt;code&gt;glab username&lt;/code&gt;, we can create a new &lt;code&gt;origin&lt;/code&gt; URL for the current Git repository with our &lt;code&gt;username&lt;/code&gt; on GitLab.com. Pushing to a new remote URL &lt;a href=&#34;https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-write-bash-one-liners-for-cloning-and-managing-github-and-gitlab-repositories/#a-bash-one-liner-to-create-and-push-many-repositories-on-gitlab&#34;&gt;automatically creates a new private GitLab repository&lt;/a&gt;, so this is a useful shortcut for creating backups!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bash functions are really only limited by the possibilities of scripting, of which there are, practically, few limits. If there&amp;rsquo;s anything we do on a frequent basis that requires typing a few lines into a terminal, we can probably create a Bash function for it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;bash-prompt&#34;&gt;Bash prompt&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides directory contents, it&amp;rsquo;s also useful to see the full path of the directory we&amp;rsquo;re in. The Bash prompt can show us this path, along with other useful information like our current Git branch. To make it more readable, we can define colours for each part of the prompt. Here&amp;rsquo;s how we can set up our prompt in &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; to accomplish this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Colour codes are cumbersome, so let&amp;#39;s name them&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;txtcyn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;\[\e[0;96m\]&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Cyan&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;txtpur&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;\[\e[0;35m\]&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Purple&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;txtwht&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;\[\e[0;37m\]&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# White&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;txtrst&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;\[\e[0m\]&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Text Reset&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Which (C)olour for what part of the prompt?&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;pathC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;txtcyn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;gitC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;txtpur&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;pointerC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;txtwht&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;normalC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;txtrst&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Get the name of our branch and put parenthesis around it&lt;/span&gt;
gitBranch&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
git branch &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&amp;gt; /dev/null &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; sed -e &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;/^[^*]/d&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; -e &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;s/* \(.*\)/(\1)/&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Build the prompt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;PS1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;pathC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;\w &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;gitC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;\$(gitBranch) &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;pointerC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;\$&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;normalC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt; &amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Result:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;~/github/myrepo &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;master&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; $&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naming the colours helps to easily identify where one colour starts and stops, and where the next one begins. The prompt that we see in our terminal is defined by the string following &lt;code&gt;export PS1&lt;/code&gt;, with each component of the prompt set with an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/Bash-Prompt-HOWTO/bash-prompt-escape-sequences.html&#34;&gt;escape sequence&lt;/a&gt;. Let&amp;rsquo;s break that down:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\w&lt;/code&gt; displays the current working directory,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\$(gitBranch)&lt;/code&gt; calls the &lt;code&gt;gitBranch&lt;/code&gt; function defined above, which displays the current Git branch,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\$&lt;/code&gt; will display a &amp;ldquo;$&amp;rdquo; if you are a normal user or in normal user mode, and a &amp;ldquo;#&amp;rdquo; if you are root.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/bash/manual/html_node/Controlling-the-Prompt.html&#34;&gt;full list of Bash escape sequences&lt;/a&gt; can help us display many more bits of information, including even the time and date! Bash prompts are highly customizable and individual, so feel free to set it up any way you please.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are a few options that put information front and centre and can help us to work more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-the-procrastination-averse&#34;&gt;For the procrastination-averse&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Username and current time with seconds, in 24-hour HH:MM:SS format:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;PS1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;userC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;\u &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;normalC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;at \t &amp;gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;user at 09:35:55 &amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-those-who-always-like-to-know-where-they-stand&#34;&gt;For those who always like to know where they stand&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Full file path on a separate line, and username:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;PS1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;pathC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;\w&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;${&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;normalC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;si&#34;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;\n\u:&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;~/github/myrepo
user:
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;for-the-minimalist&#34;&gt;For the minimalist&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;export&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;PS1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;&amp;gt;&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can build many practical prompts with just the basic escape sequences; once we start to integrate functions with prompts, as in the Git branch example, things can get really complicated. Whether this amount of complication is an addition or a detriment to your productivity, only you can know for sure!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many fancy Bash prompts are possible with programs readily available with a quick search. I&amp;rsquo;ve intentionally not provided samples here because, well, if you can tend to get as excited about this stuff as I can, it might be a couple hours before you get back to what you were doing before you started reading this post, and I just can&amp;rsquo;t have that on my conscience. 🥺&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve hopefully struck a nice balance now between time invested and usefulness gained from our Bash configuration file! I hope you use your newly-recovered keystroke capacity for good.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><enclosure url="https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-do-twice-as-much-with-half-the-keystrokes-using-.bashrc/cover_huc91640f9694e31ff03eab28f9c840023_19597_640x0_resize_box_2.png" type="image/jpg"/></item><item><title>How to set up a fresh Ubuntu desktop using only dotfiles and bash scripts</title><link>https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-set-up-a-fresh-ubuntu-desktop-using-only-dotfiles-and-bash-scripts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 07:58:18 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-set-up-a-fresh-ubuntu-desktop-using-only-dotfiles-and-bash-scripts/</guid><description>Configure settings, install programs, and customize your desktop environment with a single bash command.</description><content:encoded>
&lt;img src="https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-set-up-a-fresh-ubuntu-desktop-using-only-dotfiles-and-bash-scripts/cover_hu7503ff9e94bb9ad2ad596a79338ed3ec_587274_640x0_resize_q75_box.jpg" width="640" height="354"/>
&lt;p&gt;One of my most favourite things about open source files on GitHub is the ability to see how others do (what some people might call) mundane things, like set up their &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; and other dotfiles. While I&amp;rsquo;m not as enthusiastic about ricing as I was when I first came to the Linux side, I still get pretty excited when I find a config setting that makes things prettier and faster, and thus, better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently came across a few such things, particularly in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tomnomnom&#34;&gt;Tom Hudson&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; dotfiles. Tom seems to like to script things, and some of those things include automatically setting up symlinks, and installing Ubuntu repository applications and other programs. This got me thinking. Could I automate the set up of a new machine to replicate my current one?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being someone generally inclined to take things apart in order to see how they work, I know I&amp;rsquo;ve messed up my laptop on occasion. (Usually when I&amp;rsquo;m away from home, and my backup harddrive isn&amp;rsquo;t.) On those rare but really inconvenient situations when my computer becomes a shell of its former self, (ba-dum-ching) it&amp;rsquo;d be quite nice to have a fast, simple way of putting Humpty Dumpty back together again, just the way I like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In contrast to creating a &lt;a href=&#34;https://askubuntu.com/questions/19901/how-to-make-a-disk-image-and-restore-from-it-later&#34;&gt;disk image and restoring it later&lt;/a&gt;, a collection of bash scripts is easier to create, maintain, and move around. They require no special utilities, only an external transportation method. It&amp;rsquo;s like passing along the recipe, instead of the whole bundt cake. (Mmm, cake.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally, functionality like this would be super useful when setting up a virtual machine, or VM, or even just a virtual private server, or VPS. (Both of which, now that I write this, would probably make more forgiving targets for my more destructive experimentations&amp;hellip; live and learn!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, after some grepping and Googling and digging around, I now have a suite of scripts that can do this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;video controls=&#34;controls&#34; poster=&#34;cover.jpg&#34;&gt;
&lt;source src=&#34;setup.mp4&#34; type=&#34;video/mp4&#34; /&gt;
&lt;/video&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the tail end of a test run of the set up scripts on a fresh Ubuntu desktop, loaded off a bootable USB. It had all my programs and settings restored in under three minutes!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post will cover how to achieve the automatic set up of a computer running Ubuntu Desktop (in my case, Ubuntu LTS 18.04) using bash scripts. The majority of the information covered is applicable to all the Linux desktop flavours, though some syntax may differ. The bash scripts cover three main areas: linking dotfiles, installing software from Ubuntu and elsewhere, and setting up the desktop environment. We&amp;rsquo;ll cover each of these areas and go over the important bits so that you can begin to craft your own scripts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;dotfiles&#34;&gt;Dotfiles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dotfiles are what most Linux enthusiasts call configuration files. They typically live in the user&amp;rsquo;s home directory (denoted in bash scripts with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/internal.html#BUILTINREF&#34;&gt;builtin&lt;/a&gt; variable &lt;code&gt;$HOME&lt;/code&gt;) and control the appearance and behaviour of all kinds of programs. The file names begin with &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt;, which denotes hidden files in Linux (hence &amp;ldquo;dot&amp;rdquo; files). Here are some common dotfiles and ways in which they&amp;rsquo;re useful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bashrc&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; file is a list of commands executed at startup by interactive, non-login shells. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.tldp.org/LDP/abs/html/intandnonint.html&#34;&gt;Interactive vs non-interactive shells&lt;/a&gt; can be a little confusing, but aren&amp;rsquo;t necessary for us to worry about here. For our purposes, any time you open a new terminal, see a prompt, and can type commands into it, your &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; was executed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lines in this file can help improve your workflow by creating aliases that reduce keystrokes, or by displaying a helpful prompt with useful information. It can even run user-created programs, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/victoriadrake/eddie-terminal&#34;&gt;Eddie&lt;/a&gt;. For more ideas, you can have a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/victoriadrake/dotfiles/blob/master/.bashrc&#34;&gt;my &lt;code&gt;.bashrc&lt;/code&gt; file on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;vimrc&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt; dotfile configures the champion of all text editors, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.vim.org/about.php&#34;&gt;Vim&lt;/a&gt;. (If you haven&amp;rsquo;t yet wielded the powers of the keyboard shortcuts, I highly recommend &lt;a href=&#34;https://vim-adventures.com/&#34;&gt;a fun game to learn Vim with&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt;, we can set editor preferences such as display settings, colours, and custom keyboard shortcuts. You can take a look at &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/victoriadrake/dotfiles/blob/master/.vimrc&#34;&gt;my &lt;code&gt;.vimrc&lt;/code&gt; on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other dotfiles may be useful depending on the programs you use, such as &lt;code&gt;.gitconfig&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;.tmux.conf&lt;/code&gt;. Exploring dotfiles on GitHub is a great way to get a sense of what&amp;rsquo;s available and useful to you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;linking-dotfiles&#34;&gt;Linking dotfiles&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can use a script to create symbolic links, or &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Symbolic_link#POSIX_and_Unix-like_operating_systems&#34;&gt;symlinks&lt;/a&gt; for all our dotfiles. This allows us to keep all the files in a central repository, where they can easily be managed, while also providing a sort of placeholder in the spot that our programs expect the configuration file to be found. This is typically, but not always, the user home directory. For example, since I store my dotfiles on GitHub, I keep them in a directory with a path like &lt;code&gt;~/github/dotfiles/&lt;/code&gt; while the files themselves are symlinked, resulting in a path like &lt;code&gt;~/.vimrc&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To programmatically check for and handle any existing files and symlinks, then create new ones, we can use &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/victoriadrake/dotfiles/blob/master/scripts/symlink.sh&#34;&gt;this elegant shell script&lt;/a&gt;. I compliment it only because I blatantly stole the core of it from &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tomnomnom/dotfiles/blob/master/setup.sh&#34;&gt;Tom&amp;rsquo;s setup script&lt;/a&gt;, so I can&amp;rsquo;t take the credit for how lovely it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;code&gt;symlink.sh&lt;/code&gt; script works by attempting to create symlinks for each dotfile in our &lt;code&gt;$HOME&lt;/code&gt;. It first checks to see if a symlink already exists, or if a regular file or directory with the same name exists. In the former case, the symlink is removed and remade; in the latter, the file or directory is renamed, then the symlink is made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;installing-software&#34;&gt;Installing software&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the beautiful things about exploring shell scripts is discovering how much can be achieved using only the command line. As someone whose first exposure to computers was through a graphical operating system, I find working in the terminal to be refreshingly fast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With Ubuntu, most programs we likely require are available through the default Ubuntu software repositories. We typically search for these with the command &lt;code&gt;apt search &amp;lt;program&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and install them with &lt;code&gt;sudo apt install &amp;lt;program&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;. Some software we&amp;rsquo;d like may not be in the default repositories, or may not be offered there in the most current version. In these cases, we can still install these programs in Ubuntu using a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ubuntu#Package_Archives&#34;&gt;PPA, or Personal Package Archive&lt;/a&gt;. We&amp;rsquo;ll just have to be careful that the PPAs we choose are from the official sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If a program we&amp;rsquo;d like doesn&amp;rsquo;t appear in the default repositories or doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem to have a PPA, we may still be able to install it via command line. A quick search for &amp;ldquo;&lt;program&gt; installation command line&amp;rdquo; should get some answers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since bash scripts are just a collection of commands that we could run individually in the terminal, creating a script to install all our desired programs is as straightforward as putting all the commands into a script file. I chose to organize my installation scripts between the default repositories, which are installed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/victoriadrake/dotfiles/blob/master/scripts/aptinstall.sh&#34;&gt;my &lt;code&gt;aptinstall.sh&lt;/code&gt; script&lt;/a&gt;, and programs that involve external sources, handled with &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/victoriadrake/dotfiles/blob/master/scripts/programs.sh&#34;&gt;my &lt;code&gt;programs.sh&lt;/code&gt; script&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;setting-up-the-desktop-environment&#34;&gt;Setting up the desktop environment&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the recent occasions when I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten a fresh desktop (intentionally or otherwise) I always seem to forget how long it takes to remember, find, and then change all the desktop environment settings. Keyboard shortcuts, workspaces, sound settings, night mode&amp;hellip; it adds up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, all these settings have to be stored somewhere in a non-graphical format, which means that if we can discover how that&amp;rsquo;s done, we can likely find a way to easily manipulate the settings with a bash script. Lo and behold the terminal command, &lt;code&gt;gsettings list-recursively&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a heck of a lot of settings for GNOME desktop environment. We can make the list easier to scroll through (if, like me, you&amp;rsquo;re sometimes the type of person to say &amp;ldquo;Just let me look at everything and figure out what I want!&amp;rdquo;) by piping to &lt;code&gt;less&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;gsettings list-recursively | less&lt;/code&gt;. Alternatively, if we have an inkling as to what we might be looking for, we can use &lt;code&gt;grep&lt;/code&gt;: &lt;code&gt;gsettings list-recursively | grep &#39;keyboard&#39;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can manipulate our settings with the &lt;code&gt;gsettings set&lt;/code&gt; command. It can sometimes be difficult to find the syntax for the setting we want, so when we&amp;rsquo;re first building our script, I recommend using the GUI to make the changes, then finding the &lt;code&gt;gsettings&lt;/code&gt; line we changed and recording its value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some inspiration, you can view &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/victoriadrake/dotfiles/blob/master/scripts/desktop.sh&#34;&gt;my &lt;code&gt;desktop.sh&lt;/code&gt; settings script on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;putting-it-all-together&#34;&gt;Putting it all together&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having modular scripts (one for symlinks, two for installing programs, another for desktop settings) is useful for both keeping things organized and for being able to run some but not all of the automated set up. For instance, if I were to set up a VPS in which I only use the command line, I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t need to bother with installing graphical programs or desktop settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In cases where I do want to run all the scripts, however, doing so one-by-one is a little tedious. Thankfully, since bash scripts can themselves be run by terminal commands, we can simply write another master script to run them all!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s my master script to handle the set up of a new Ubuntu desktop machine:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;#!/bin/bash
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;cp&#34;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
./symlink.sh
./aptinstall.sh
./programs.sh
./desktop.sh
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Get all upgrades&lt;/span&gt;
sudo apt upgrade -y
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# See our bash changes&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;source&lt;/span&gt; ~/.bashrc
&lt;span class=&#34;c1&#34;&gt;# Fun hello&lt;/span&gt;
figlet &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;... and we&amp;#39;re back!&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; lolcat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I threw in the upgrade line for good measure. It will make sure that the programs installed on our fresh desktop have the latest updates. Now a simple, single bash command will take care of everything!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed that, while our desktop now looks and runs familiarly, these scripts don&amp;rsquo;t cover one very important area: our files. Hopefully, you have a back up method for those that involves some form of reliable external hardware. If not, and if you tend to put your work in external repository hosts like GitHub or GitLab, I do have a way to &lt;a href=&#34;https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-write-bash-one-liners-for-cloning-and-managing-github-and-gitlab-repositories/&#34;&gt;automatically clone and back up your GitHub repositories with bash one-liners&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relying on external repository hosts doesn&amp;rsquo;t offer 100% coverage, however. Files that you wouldn&amp;rsquo;t put in an externally hosted repository (private or otherwise) consequently can&amp;rsquo;t be pulled. Git ignored objects that can&amp;rsquo;t be generated from included files, like private keys and secrets, will not be recreated. Those files, however, are likely small enough that you could fit a whole bunch on a couple encrypted USB flash drives (and if you don&amp;rsquo;t have private key backups, maybe you ought to do that first?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, I hope this post has given you at least some inspiration as to how dotfiles and bash scripts can help to automate setting up a fresh desktop. If you come up with some settings you find useful, please help others discover them by sharing your dotfiles, too!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><enclosure url="https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-set-up-a-fresh-ubuntu-desktop-using-only-dotfiles-and-bash-scripts/cover_hu7503ff9e94bb9ad2ad596a79338ed3ec_587274_640x0_resize_q75_box.jpg" type="image/jpg"/></item><item><title>How to write Bash one-liners for cloning and managing GitHub and GitLab repositories</title><link>https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-write-bash-one-liners-for-cloning-and-managing-github-and-gitlab-repositories/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 10:55:19 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-write-bash-one-liners-for-cloning-and-managing-github-and-gitlab-repositories/</guid><description>Using xargs and awk in Bash to automate managing remote-hosted repositories.</description><content:encoded>
&lt;img src="https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-write-bash-one-liners-for-cloning-and-managing-github-and-gitlab-repositories/cover_hue964d861d1f646dadaea936b29727a7c_1082491_640x0_resize_box_2.png" width="640" height="343"/>
&lt;p&gt;Few things are more satisfying to me than one elegant line of Bash that automates hours of tedious work. As part of some recent explorations into automatically re-creating my laptop with Bash scripts (post to come!), I wanted to find a way to easily clone my GitHub-hosted repositories to a new machine. After a bit of digging around, I wrote a one-liner that did just that. Then, in the spirit of not putting all our eggs in the same basket, I wrote another one-liner to automatically create and push to GitLab-hosted backups as well. Here they are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-bash-one-liner-to-clone-all-your-github-repositories&#34;&gt;A Bash one-liner to clone all your GitHub repositories&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caveat: you&amp;rsquo;ll need a list of the GitHub repositories you want to clone. The good thing about that is it gives you full agency to choose just the repositories you want on your machine, instead of going in whole-hog.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can easily clone GitHub repositories without entering your password each time by using HTTPS with your &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/articles/caching-your-github-password-in-git&#34;&gt;15-minute cached credentials&lt;/a&gt; or, my preferred method, by &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/articles/connecting-to-github-with-ssh&#34;&gt;connecting to GitHub with SSH&lt;/a&gt;. For brevity I&amp;rsquo;ll assume we&amp;rsquo;re going with the latter, and our SSH keys are set up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given a list of GitHub URLs in the file &lt;code&gt;gh-repos.txt&lt;/code&gt;, like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-txt&#34; data-lang=&#34;txt&#34;&gt;git@github.com:username/first-repository.git
git@github.com:username/second-repository.git
git@github.com:username/third-repository.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We run:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;xargs -n1 git clone &amp;lt; gh-repos.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This clones all the repositories on the list into the current folder. This same one-liner works for GitLab repositories as well, if you substitute the appropriate URLs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-going-on-here&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s going on here?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two halves to this one-liner: the input, counterintuitively on the right side, and the part that makes stuff happen, on the left. We could make the order of these parts more intuitive (maybe?) by writing the same command like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&amp;lt;gh-repos.txt xargs -n1 git clone &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run a command for each line of our input, &lt;code&gt;gh-repos.txt&lt;/code&gt;, we use &lt;code&gt;xargs -n1&lt;/code&gt;. The tool &lt;code&gt;xargs&lt;/code&gt; reads items from input and executes any commands it finds (it will &lt;code&gt;echo&lt;/code&gt; if it doesn&amp;rsquo;t find any). By default, it assumes that items are separated by spaces; new lines also works and makes our list easier to read. The flag &lt;code&gt;-n1&lt;/code&gt; tells &lt;code&gt;xargs&lt;/code&gt; to use &lt;code&gt;1&lt;/code&gt; argument, or in our case, one line, per command. We build our command with &lt;code&gt;git clone&lt;/code&gt;, which &lt;code&gt;xargs&lt;/code&gt; then executes for each line. Ta-da.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-bash-one-liner-to-create-and-push-many-repositories-on-gitlab&#34;&gt;A Bash one-liner to create and push many repositories on GitLab&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitLab, unlike GitHub, lets us do this nifty thing where we don&amp;rsquo;t have to use the website to make a new repository first. We can &lt;a href=&#34;https://gitlab.com/help/gitlab-basics/create-project#push-to-create-a-new-project&#34;&gt;create a new GitLab repository from our terminal&lt;/a&gt;. The newly created repository defaults to being set as Private, so if we want to make it Public on GitLab, we&amp;rsquo;ll have to do that manually later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GitLab docs tell us to push to create a new project using &lt;code&gt;git push --set-upstream&lt;/code&gt;, but I don&amp;rsquo;t find this to be very convenient for using GitLab as a backup. As I work with my repositories in the future, I&amp;rsquo;d like to run one command that pushes to both GitHub &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; GitLab without additional effort on my part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make this Bash one-liner work, we&amp;rsquo;ll also need a list of repository URLs for GitLab (ones that don&amp;rsquo;t exist yet). We can easily do this by copying our GitHub repository list, opening it up with Vim, and doing a &lt;a href=&#34;https://vim.fandom.com/wiki/Search_and_replace&#34;&gt;search-and-replace&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;cp gh-repos.txt gl-repos.txt
vim gl-repos.txt
:%s/&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;github&lt;span class=&#34;se&#34;&gt;\&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;/gitlab/g
:wq&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This produces &lt;code&gt;gl-repos.txt&lt;/code&gt;, which looks like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-txt&#34; data-lang=&#34;txt&#34;&gt;git@gitlab.com:username/first-repository.git
git@gitlab.com:username/second-repository.git
git@gitlab.com:username/third-repository.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can create these repositories on GitLab, add the URLs as remotes, and push our code to the new repositories by running:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;awk -F&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;\/|(\.git)&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;{system(&amp;#34;cd ~/FULL/PATH/&amp;#34; $2 &amp;#34; &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git remote set-url origin --add &amp;#34; $0 &amp;#34; &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git push&amp;#34;)}&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; gl-repos.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hang tight and I&amp;rsquo;ll explain it; for now, take note that &lt;code&gt;~/FULL/PATH/&lt;/code&gt; should be the full path to the directory containing our GitHub repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We do have to make note of a couple assumptions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The name of the directory on your local machine that contains the repository is the same as the name of the repository in the URL (this will be the case if it was cloned with the one-liner above);&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each repository is currently checked out to the branch you want pushed, ie. &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one-liner could be expanded to handle these assumptions, but it is the humble opinion of the author that at that point, we really ought to be writing a Bash script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-s-going-on-here-1&#34;&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s going on here?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our Bash one-liner uses each line (or URL) in the &lt;code&gt;gl-repos.txt&lt;/code&gt; file as input. With &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt;, it splits off the name of the directory containing the repository on our local machine, and uses these pieces of information to build our larger command. If we were to &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; the output of &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt;, we&amp;rsquo;d see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/FULL/PATH/first-repository &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; git remote set-url origin --add git@gitlab.com:username/first-repository.git &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; git push
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/FULL/PATH/second-repository &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; git remote set-url origin --add git@gitlab.com:username/second-repository.git &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; git push
&lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;cd&lt;/span&gt; ~/FULL/PATH/third-repository &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; git remote set-url origin --add git@gitlab.com:username/third-repository.git &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; git push&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s look at how we build this command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;splitting-strings-with-awk&#34;&gt;Splitting strings with &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; can split input based on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/gawk/manual/html_node/Command-Line-Field-Separator.html&#34;&gt;field separators&lt;/a&gt;. The default separator is a whitespace character, but we can change this by passing the &lt;code&gt;-F&lt;/code&gt; flag. Besides single characters, we can also use a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/gawk/manual/html_node/Regexp-Field-Splitting.html#Regexp-Field-Splitting&#34;&gt;regular expression field separator&lt;/a&gt;. Since our repository URLs have a set format, we can grab the repository names by asking for the substring between the slash character &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; and the end of the URL, &lt;code&gt;.git&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way to accomplish this is with our regex &lt;code&gt;\/|(\.git)&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;\/&lt;/code&gt; is an escaped &lt;code&gt;/&lt;/code&gt; character;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt; means &amp;ldquo;or&amp;rdquo;, telling awk to match either expression;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;(\.git)&lt;/code&gt; is the capture group at the end of our URL that matches &amp;ldquo;.git&amp;rdquo;, with an escaped &lt;code&gt;.&lt;/code&gt; character. This is a bit of a cheat, as &amp;ldquo;.git&amp;rdquo; isn&amp;rsquo;t strictly splitting anything (there&amp;rsquo;s nothing on the other side) but it&amp;rsquo;s an easy way for us to take this bit off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we&amp;rsquo;ve told &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; where to split, we can grab the right substring with the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.gnu.org/software/gawk/manual/html_node/Fields.html#index-_0024-_0028dollar-sign_0029_002c-_0024-field-operator&#34;&gt;field operator&lt;/a&gt;. We refer to our fields with a &lt;code&gt;$&lt;/code&gt; character, then by the field&amp;rsquo;s column number. In our example, we want the second field, &lt;code&gt;$2&lt;/code&gt;. Here&amp;rsquo;s what all the substrings look like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;: git@gitlab.com:username
&lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;: first-repository&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To use the whole string, or in our case, the whole URL, we use the field operator &lt;code&gt;$0&lt;/code&gt;. To write the command, we just substitute the field operators for the repository name and URL. Running this with &lt;code&gt;print&lt;/code&gt; as we&amp;rsquo;re building it can help to make sure we&amp;rsquo;ve got all the spaces right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;awk -F&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;\/|(\.git)&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;{print &amp;#34;cd ~/FULL/PATH/&amp;#34; $2 &amp;#34; &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git remote set-url origin --add &amp;#34; $0 &amp;#34; &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git push&amp;#34;}&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; gl-repos.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;running-the-command&#34;&gt;Running the command&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We build our command inside the parenthesis of &lt;code&gt;system()&lt;/code&gt;. By using this as the output of &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt;, each command will run as soon as it is built and output. The &lt;code&gt;system()&lt;/code&gt; function creates a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Child_process&#34;&gt;child process&lt;/a&gt; that executes our command, then returns once the command is completed. In plain English, this lets us perform the Git commands on each repository, one-by-one, without breaking from our main process in which &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; is doing things with our input file. Here&amp;rsquo;s our final command again, all put together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;awk -F&lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;\/|(\.git)&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;{system(&amp;#34;cd ~/FULL/PATH/&amp;#34; $2 &amp;#34; &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git remote set-url origin --add &amp;#34; $0 &amp;#34; &amp;amp;&amp;amp; git push&amp;#34;)}&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; gl-repos.txt&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;using-our-backups&#34;&gt;Using our backups&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By adding the GitLab URLs as remotes, we&amp;rsquo;ve simplified the process of pushing to both externally hosted repositories. If we run &lt;code&gt;git remote -v&lt;/code&gt; in one of our repository directories, we&amp;rsquo;ll see:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;origin git@github.com:username/first-repository.git &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;fetch&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
origin git@github.com:username/first-repository.git &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;push&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
origin git@gitlab.com:username/first-repository.git &lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;push&lt;span class=&#34;o&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, simply running &lt;code&gt;git push&lt;/code&gt; without arguments will push the current branch to both remote repositories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should also note that &lt;code&gt;git pull&lt;/code&gt; will generally only try to pull from the remote repository you originally cloned from (the URL marked &lt;code&gt;(fetch)&lt;/code&gt; in our example above). Pulling from multiple Git repositories at the same time is possible, but complicated, and beyond the scope of this post. Here&amp;rsquo;s an &lt;a href=&#34;https://astrofloyd.wordpress.com/2015/05/05/git-pushing-to-and-pulling-from-multiple-remote-locations-remote-url-and-pushurl/&#34;&gt;explanation of pushing and pulling to multiple remotes&lt;/a&gt; to help get you started, if you&amp;rsquo;re curious. The &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/book/en/v2/Git-Basics-Working-with-Remotes&#34;&gt;Git documentation on remotes&lt;/a&gt; may also be helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;to-elaborate-on-the-succinctness-of-bash-one-liners&#34;&gt;To elaborate on the succinctness of Bash one-liners&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bash one-liners, when understood, can be fun and handy shortcuts. At the very least, being aware of tools like &lt;code&gt;xargs&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; can help to automate and alleviate a lot of tediousness in our work. However, there are some downsides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of an easy-to-understand, maintainable, and approachable tool, Bash one-liners suck. They&amp;rsquo;re usually more complicated to write than a Bash script using &lt;code&gt;if&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;while&lt;/code&gt; loops, and certainly more complicated to read. It&amp;rsquo;s likely that when we write them, we&amp;rsquo;ll miss a single quote or closing parenthesis somewhere; and as I hope this post demonstrates, they can take quite a bit of explaining, too. So why use them?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine reading a recipe for baking a cake, step by step. You understand the methods and ingredients, and gather your supplies. Then, as you think about it, you begin to realize that if you just throw all the ingredients at the oven in precisely the right order, a cake will instantly materialize. You try it, and it works!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That would be pretty satisfying, wouldn&amp;rsquo;t it?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><enclosure url="https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-write-bash-one-liners-for-cloning-and-managing-github-and-gitlab-repositories/cover_hue964d861d1f646dadaea936b29727a7c_1082491_640x0_resize_box_2.png" type="image/jpg"/></item><item><title>A quick guide to changing your GitHub username</title><link>https://victoria.dev/verbose/a-quick-guide-to-changing-your-github-username/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 15:19:13 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/verbose/a-quick-guide-to-changing-your-github-username/</guid><description>Some additional steps to consider after making a change to your username on GitHub.</description><content:encoded>
&lt;img src="https://victoria.dev/verbose/a-quick-guide-to-changing-your-github-username/cover_hu7812c3e32a841cc1ab09568139e9132c_71747_640x0_resize_box_2.png" width="640" height="421"/>
&lt;p&gt;This being the 2,38947234th and probably last time I&amp;rsquo;ll change my username, (marriage is permanent, right?) I thought I&amp;rsquo;d better write a quick post on how this transition can be achieved as smoothly as possible. You can read &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/articles/changing-your-github-username&#34;&gt;official instructions on how to change your GitHub username&lt;/a&gt; here, and they will tell you how to do it and what happens. The following is a quick guide to some things to consider &lt;em&gt;afterwards.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;where-to-make-changes&#34;&gt;Where to make changes&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Change username in &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/settings/admin&#34;&gt;GitHub account settings.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If using GitHub Pages, change name of your &amp;ldquo;username.github.io&amp;rdquo; repository.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If using other services that point to your &amp;ldquo;username.github.io&amp;rdquo; repository address, update them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If using Netlify, you &lt;em&gt;may&lt;/em&gt; want to sign in and reconnect your repositories. (Mine still worked, but due to a possibly unrelated issue, I&amp;rsquo;m not positive.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sign in to Travis CI and other integrations (find them in your repository Settings tab -&amp;gt; Integrations &amp;amp; services). This will update your username there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Update your local files and repository links with &lt;em&gt;very carefully executed&lt;/em&gt; &lt;code&gt;find&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt; commands, and push back changes to GitHub.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redeploy any websites you may have with your updated GitHub link.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fix any links around the web to your profile, your repositories, or Gists you may have shared.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;local-file-updates&#34;&gt;Local file updates&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some suggestions for strings to search and replace your username in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;github.com/username&lt;/code&gt; (References to your GitHub page in READMEs or in website copy)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;username.github.io&lt;/code&gt; (Links to your GitHub Page)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;git@github.com:username&lt;/code&gt; (Git config remote ssh urls)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;travis-ci.com/username&lt;/code&gt; (Travis badges in READMEs)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;shields.io/github/.../username&lt;/code&gt; (Shields badges in READMEs, types include &lt;code&gt;contributors&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;stars&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;tags&lt;/code&gt;, and more)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can quickly identify where the above strings are located using this command for each string:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;grep -rnw -e &#39;foobar&#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will recursively (&lt;code&gt;r&lt;/code&gt;) search all files for strings matching the whole (&lt;code&gt;w&lt;/code&gt;) pattern (&lt;code&gt;e&lt;/code&gt;) provided and prefix results with the line numbers (&lt;code&gt;n&lt;/code&gt;) so you can easily find them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;code&gt;find&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;sed&lt;/code&gt; can make these changes much faster. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-to-replace-a-string-in-a-dozen-old-blog-posts-with-one-sed-terminal-command/&#34;&gt;this article on search and replace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy your new handle! (I hope it sticks.)&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><enclosure url="https://victoria.dev/verbose/a-quick-guide-to-changing-your-github-username/cover_hu7812c3e32a841cc1ab09568139e9132c_71747_640x0_resize_box_2.png" type="image/jpg"/></item><item><title>A remote sync solution for iOS and Linux: Git and Working Copy</title><link>https://victoria.dev/verbose/a-remote-sync-solution-for-ios-and-linux-git-and-working-copy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 11:55:28 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/verbose/a-remote-sync-solution-for-ios-and-linux-git-and-working-copy/</guid><description>How to set up a cross-platform cloud sync solution for working anywhere using Git on iOS.</description><content:encoded>
&lt;img src="https://victoria.dev/verbose/a-remote-sync-solution-for-ios-and-linux-git-and-working-copy/cover_remote-sync_hu1984111f2d75b603219adcc3d215dc57_618766_640x0_resize_box_2.png" width="640" height="418"/>
&lt;p&gt;I previously wrote about a (hackish) way to use a &lt;a href=&#34;https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-i-set-up-a-single-dropbox-folder-on-my-dual-boot-windows-and-linux-system/&#34;&gt;single Dropbox folder on a dual-boot Windows and Linux machine&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;ve since &lt;del&gt;gained some sense&lt;/del&gt; gone full Linux with Ubuntu 18.04 LTS, but the Dropbox set up seems to have stopped being an option in any case. Fortunately, I&amp;rsquo;ve since found a much better (far less hackish) way to remote-sync files across different file systems. Reflecting my current set up, I&amp;rsquo;m talking about iOS (iPad and iPhone) and my Linux machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new sync system is based on Git, very customizable, and conveniently extensible. Beyond text files, you can sync anything that Git can (which is almost everything - if you want to edit your &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt;d files on the go I&amp;rsquo;m not sure I can help). If you&amp;rsquo;re already familiar with Git, getting set up will be a walk in the park. If Git is new to you, I think these tools help make the concepts of Git cloning, pulling, and pushing straightforward to understand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;components&#34;&gt;Components&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://workingcopy.app&#34;&gt;Working Copy app&lt;/a&gt; ($15.99 one-time pro-unlock and well worth it, iOS only)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://ia.net/writer&#34;&gt;iA Writer app&lt;/a&gt; ($8.99 one-time purchase for iOS, also available on Mac, Windows, and Android)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;GitHub repositories (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.blog/2019-01-07-new-year-new-github/&#34;&gt;private&lt;/a&gt; or public, both free)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was inspired by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.macstories.net/ios/my-markdown-writing-and-collaboration-workflow-powered-by-working-copy-3-6-icloud-drive-and-github/&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; as well as &lt;a href=&#34;http://blog.joncairns.com/2011/10/how-to-use-git-submodules/&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;get-set-up&#34;&gt;Get set up&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the steps to setting up that I&amp;rsquo;ll walk you through in this article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create your remote repository&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clone repository to iPad with Working Copy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Open and edit files with iA Writer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Push changes back to remote&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pull changes from repository on your computer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This system is straightforward to set up whether you&amp;rsquo;re a command line whiz or just getting into Git. Let&amp;rsquo;s do it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;create-your-remote-repository&#34;&gt;Create your remote repository&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GitHub now offers free &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.blog/2019-01-07-new-year-new-github/&#34;&gt;private repositories&lt;/a&gt; for up to three collaborators. Choose &amp;ldquo;Private&amp;rdquo; on GitHub&amp;rsquo;s repository creation page:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;github-private-repo.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Selection options for public and private repository&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Create the repository. If you&amp;rsquo;d like to, you can follow GitHub&amp;rsquo;s instructions to push some files to it from your computer, or you can add files later from your iPad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;clone-repository-to-ipad-with-working-copy&#34;&gt;Clone repository to iPad with Working Copy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download &lt;a href=&#34;https://workingcopy.app&#34;&gt;Working Copy&lt;/a&gt; from the App Store. It&amp;rsquo;s one of the more expensive apps I&amp;rsquo;ve purchased, but I think it&amp;rsquo;s well worth it. Developer &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/palmin&#34;&gt;Anders Borum&lt;/a&gt; has a steady track record of frequent updates and incorporating the latest features for iOS apps, like &lt;a href=&#34;https://workingcopy.app/manual/dragdrop&#34;&gt;drag and drop&lt;/a&gt; on iPad. I think he&amp;rsquo;s fairly priced his product in light of the work he puts into maintaining and enhancing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Working Copy, find the gear icon in the top left corner and touch to open Settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;workingcopy-settings.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Settings menu in Working Copy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tap on SSH Keys, and you&amp;rsquo;ll see this screen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;workingcopy-ssh.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;SSH Key for Working Copy on iPad&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SSH keys, or Secure Shell keys, are access credentials used in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secure_Shell&#34;&gt;SSH protocol&lt;/a&gt;. Your key is a password that your device will use to securely connect with your remote repository host - GitHub, in our example. Since anyone with your SSH keys can potentially pretend to be you and gain access to your files, it&amp;rsquo;s important not to share them accidentally, like in a screenshot on a blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tap on the second line that looks like &amp;ldquo;WorkingCopy@iPad-xxxxxxxx&amp;rdquo; to get this screen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;workingcopy-ssh-connect.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Connect to GitHub or Bitbucket in Working Copy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working Copy supports easy connection to both BitBucket and GitHub. Tap &amp;ldquo;Connect With GitHub&amp;rdquo; or BitBucket to bring up some familiar sign-in screens that will authorize Working Copy to access your account(s).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once connected, tap the &amp;ldquo;+&amp;rdquo; symbol in the top right of the side bar to add a new repository. Choose &amp;ldquo;Clone repository&amp;rdquo; to bring up this screen:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;workingcopy-read-repos.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Loading repositories from remote&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, you can either manually input the remote URL, or simply choose from the list of repositories that Working Copy fetches from your connected account. When you make your choice, the app clones the repository to your iPad and it will show up in the sidebar. You&amp;rsquo;re connected!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;open-and-edit-files-with-ia-writer&#34;&gt;Open and edit files with iA Writer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the (many) reasons I adore &lt;a href=&#34;https://ia.net/writer&#34;&gt;iA Writer&lt;/a&gt; is its ability to select your freshly cloned remote repository as a Library Location. To do this in the iA Writer app:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the main Library list, in the top right of the sidebar, tap &amp;ldquo;Edit&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tap &amp;ldquo;Add Location&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A helpful popup appears. Tap OK.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From the Working Copy location, tap &amp;ldquo;Select&amp;rdquo; in the top right, then choose the repository folder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tap &amp;ldquo;Open&amp;rdquo;, then &amp;ldquo;Done&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your remote repository now appears as a Location in the sidebar. Tap on it to work within this directory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While inside this location, new files you create (by tapping the pencil-and-paper icon in the top right corner) will be saved to this folder locally. As you work, iA Writer automatically saves your progress. Next, we&amp;rsquo;ll look at pushing those files and changes back to your remote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;push-changes-back-to-remote&#34;&gt;Push changes back to remote&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;ve made changes to your files, open Working Copy again. You should see a yellow dot on your changed repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;workingcopy-changed-repo.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Yellow dot indicating changes to repository&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tap on your repository name, then on &amp;ldquo;Repository Status and Configuration&amp;rdquo; at the top of the sidebar. Your changed files will be indicated by yellow dots or green &amp;ldquo;+&amp;rdquo; symbols. These mean that you&amp;rsquo;ve modified or added files, respectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Working Copy is a sweet iOS Git client, and you can tap on your files to see additional information including a comparison of changes (&amp;ldquo;diff&amp;rdquo;) as well as status and Git history. You can even edit files right within the app, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://workingcopyapp.com/manual/edit&#34;&gt;syntax highlighting&lt;/a&gt; for its many supported languages. For now, we&amp;rsquo;ll look at how to push your changed work to your remote repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;workingcopy-changes-to-commit.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Changes to commit&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the &amp;ldquo;Repository Status and Configuration&amp;rdquo; page, you&amp;rsquo;ll see right at the top that there are changes to be committed. If you&amp;rsquo;re new to Git, this is like &amp;ldquo;saving your changes&amp;rdquo; to your Git history, something typically done with the terminal command &lt;a href=&#34;https://git-scm.com/docs/git-commit&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;git commit&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. You can think of this as saving the files that we&amp;rsquo;ll want to send to the GitHub repository. Tap &amp;ldquo;Commit changes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;workingcopy-commit-changes.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Add a commit message and select files to commit&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter your commit message, and select the files you want to add. Turn on the &amp;ldquo;Push&amp;rdquo; switch to send everything to your remote repository when you commit the files. Then tap &amp;ldquo;Commit.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll see a progress bar as your files are uploaded, and then a confirmation message on the status screen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;workingcopy-commit-success.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;Commit success message&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Congratulations! Your changes are now present in your remote repository on GitHub. You&amp;rsquo;ve successfully synced your files remotely!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;pull-changes-from-repository-on-your-computer&#34;&gt;Pull changes from repository on your computer&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To bring your updated files full circle to your computer, you pull them from the GitHub repository. I prefer to use the terminal for this as it&amp;rsquo;s quick and easy, but GitHub also offers a &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/desktop/getting-started-with-github-desktop&#34;&gt;graphical client&lt;/a&gt; if terminal commands seem a little alien for now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you started with the GitHub repository, you can clone it to a folder on your computer by following &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/articles/cloning-a-repository&#34;&gt;these instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;staying-in-sync&#34;&gt;Staying in sync&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you update your work on your computer, you&amp;rsquo;ll use Git to push your changes to the remote repository. To do this, you can use GitHub&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/desktop/getting-started-with-github-desktop&#34;&gt;graphical client&lt;/a&gt;, or follow &lt;a href=&#34;https://help.github.com/en/articles/adding-an-existing-project-to-github-using-the-command-line&#34;&gt;these instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On your iOS device, Working Copy makes pulling and pushing as simple as a single tap. On the Repository Status and Configuration page, tap on the remote name under &amp;ldquo;Remotes&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;workingcopy-git-remote.png#screenshot&#34; alt=&#34;List of Remotes in Working Copy&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then tap &amp;ldquo;Synchronize&amp;rdquo;. Working Copy will take care of the details of pushing your committed changes and/or pulling any new changes it finds from the remote repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;not-bad-right&#34;&gt;Not bad, right?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a Git-based developer and work-anywhere-aholic like me, this set up couldn&amp;rsquo;t be more convenient. Working Copy really makes staying in sync with my remote repositories seamless, nevermind the ability to work with any of my GitHub repos on the go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For editing on the go, here&amp;rsquo;s a useful tip. Use &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; in your sync repository if you don&amp;rsquo;t need to move large files, like images, around with you. This will stop the ignored files from being pushed to GitHub and pulled to your iOS device - they&amp;rsquo;ll only remain on your computer&amp;rsquo;s larger hard drive. The &lt;code&gt;.gitignore&lt;/code&gt; file of one of my sync repositories looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;*.png
*.jpeg
*.jpg
*.mp4
*.gif
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This means all the media files stay on my computer, and I can pull just the text file content to my iPad from GitHub to work on while I&amp;rsquo;m out and about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I most recently used this set up to get some writing done while hanging out in the atrium of Washington DC&amp;rsquo;s National Portrait Gallery, which is pleasantly photogenic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;washington-portrait-gallery.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The atrium of the National Portrait Gallery&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/victoriadotdev&#34;&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear&lt;/a&gt; how this set up works for you and how you use it. In the meantime, happy working!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><enclosure url="https://victoria.dev/verbose/a-remote-sync-solution-for-ios-and-linux-git-and-working-copy/cover_remote-sync_hu1984111f2d75b603219adcc3d215dc57_618766_640x0_resize_box_2.png" type="image/jpg"/></item><item><title>Batch renaming images, including image resolution, with awk</title><link>https://victoria.dev/verbose/batch-renaming-images-including-image-resolution-with-awk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 13:59:30 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/verbose/batch-renaming-images-including-image-resolution-with-awk/</guid><description>How to batch rename images with custom values using file, awk, and rename - in rainbow colors!</description><content:encoded>
&lt;img src="https://victoria.dev/verbose/batch-renaming-images-including-image-resolution-with-awk/renaming-rainbow_hua6bda34c4dd82ff49a9f97483b0665f2_159523_640x0_resize_box_2.png" width="640" height="317"/>
&lt;p&gt;The most recent item on my list of &amp;ldquo;Geeky things I did that made me feel pretty awesome&amp;rdquo; is an hour&amp;rsquo;s adventure that culminated in this code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;$ file IMG* &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; awk &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;BEGIN{a=0} {print substr($1, 1, length($1)-5),a++&amp;#34;_&amp;#34;substr($8,1, length($8)-1)}&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;read&lt;/span&gt; fn fr&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;rename -v &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;s/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$fn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;/img_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$fr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;/g&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; *&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;done&lt;/span&gt;
IMG_20170808_172653_425.jpg renamed as img_0_4032x3024.jpg
IMG_20170808_173020_267.jpg renamed as img_1_3024x3506.jpg
IMG_20170808_173130_616.jpg renamed as img_2_3024x3779.jpg
IMG_20170808_173221_425.jpg renamed as img_3_3024x3780.jpg
IMG_20170808_173417_059.jpg renamed as img_4_2956x2980.jpg
IMG_20170808_173450_971.jpg renamed as img_5_3024x3024.jpg
IMG_20170808_173536_034.jpg renamed as img_6_4032x3024.jpg
IMG_20170808_173602_732.jpg renamed as img_7_1617x1617.jpg
IMG_20170808_173645_339.jpg renamed as img_8_3024x3780.jpg
IMG_20170909_170146_585.jpg renamed as img_9_3036x3036.jpg
IMG_20170911_211522_543.jpg renamed as img_10_3036x3036.jpg
IMG_20170913_071608_288.jpg renamed as img_11_2760x2760.jpg
IMG_20170913_073205_522.jpg renamed as img_12_2738x2738.jpg
// ... etc etc&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last item on the aforementioned list is &amp;ldquo;TODO: come up with a shorter title for this list.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I previously wrote about the power of command line tools like &lt;a href=&#34;https://victoria.dev/verbose/when-stackoverflow-sed-saves-30mins/&#34;&gt;sed&lt;/a&gt;. This post expands on how to string all this magical functionality into one big, long, rainbow-coloured, viscous stream of awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;rename-files&#34;&gt;Rename files&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tool that actually handles the renaming of our files is, appropriately enough, &lt;code&gt;rename&lt;/code&gt;. The syntax is: &lt;code&gt;rename -n &amp;quot;s/original_filename/new_filename/g&amp;quot; *&lt;/code&gt; where &lt;code&gt;-n&lt;/code&gt; does a dry-run, and substituting &lt;code&gt;-v&lt;/code&gt; would rename the files. The &lt;code&gt;s&lt;/code&gt; indicates our substitution string, and &lt;code&gt;g&lt;/code&gt; for &amp;ldquo;global&amp;rdquo; finds all occurrences of the string. The &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; matches zero or more occurrences of our search-and-replace parameters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll come back to this later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;get-file-information&#34;&gt;Get file information&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I run &lt;code&gt;$ file IMG_20170808_172653_425.jpg&lt;/code&gt; in the image directory, I get this output:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;IMG_20170808_172653_425.jpg: JPEG image data, baseline, precision &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;8&lt;/span&gt;, 4032x3024, frames &lt;span class=&#34;m&#34;&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we can get the image resolution (&amp;ldquo;4032x3024&amp;rdquo; above), we know that we&amp;rsquo;ll be able to use it in our new filename.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;isolate-the-information-we-want&#34;&gt;Isolate the information we want&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; for its simplicity. It takes lines of text and makes individual bits of information available to us with built in variables that we can then refer to as column numbers denoted by &lt;code&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;$2&lt;/code&gt;, etc. By default, &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; splits up columns on whitespace. To take the example above:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;| 1 | 2 | 3 | 4 | 5 | 6 | 7 | 8 | 9 | 10 |
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
| IMG_20170808_172653_425.jpg: | JPEG | image | data, | baseline, | precision | 8, | 4032x3024, | frames | 3 |
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can denote different values to use as a splitter with, for example, &lt;code&gt;-F&#39;,&#39;&lt;/code&gt; if we wanted to use commas as the column divisions. For our current project, spaces are fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple issues we need to solve before we can plug the information into our new filenames. Column &lt;code&gt;$1&lt;/code&gt; has the original filename we want, but there&amp;rsquo;s an extra &amp;ldquo;:&amp;rdquo; character on the end. We don&amp;rsquo;t need the &amp;ldquo;.jpg&amp;rdquo; either. Column &lt;code&gt;$8&lt;/code&gt; has an extra &amp;ldquo;,&amp;rdquo; that we don&amp;rsquo;t want as well. To get just to information we need, we&amp;rsquo;ll take a substring of the column with &lt;code&gt;substr()&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;substr($1, 1, length($1)-5)&lt;/code&gt; - This gives us the file name from the beginning of the string to the end of the string, minus 5 characters (&amp;ldquo;length minus 5&amp;rdquo;).
&lt;code&gt;substr($8,1, length($8)-1)&lt;/code&gt; - This gives us the image size, without the extra comma (&amp;ldquo;length minus 1&amp;rdquo;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;avoid-duplicate-file-names&#34;&gt;Avoid duplicate file names&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure that two images with the same resolutions don&amp;rsquo;t create identical, competing file names, we&amp;rsquo;ll append a unique incrementing number to the filename.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;BEGIN{a=0}&lt;/code&gt; - Using &lt;code&gt;BEGIN&lt;/code&gt; tells &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; to run the following code only once, at the (drumroll) beginning. Here, we&amp;rsquo;re declaring the variable &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; to be &lt;code&gt;0&lt;/code&gt;.
&lt;code&gt;a++&lt;/code&gt; - Later in our code, at the appropriate spot for our file name, we call &lt;code&gt;a&lt;/code&gt; and increment it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; prints a string, it concatenates everything that isn&amp;rsquo;t separated by a comma. &lt;code&gt;{print a b c}&lt;/code&gt; would create &amp;ldquo;abc&amp;rdquo; and &lt;code&gt;{print a,b,c}&lt;/code&gt; would create &amp;ldquo;a b c&amp;rdquo;, for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can add additional characters to our file name, such as an underscore, by inserting it in quotations: &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;_&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;string-it-all-together&#34;&gt;String it all together&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To feed the output of one command into another command, we use &amp;ldquo;pipe,&amp;rdquo; written as &lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we only used pipe in this instance, all our data from &lt;code&gt;file&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; would get fed into &lt;code&gt;rename&lt;/code&gt; all at once, making for one very, very long and probably non-compiling file name. To run the &lt;code&gt;rename&lt;/code&gt; command line by line, we can use &lt;code&gt;while&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt;. Similarly to &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;read&lt;/code&gt; takes input and splits it into variables we can assign and use. In our code, it takes the first bit of output from &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; (the original file name) and assigns that the variable name &lt;code&gt;$fn&lt;/code&gt;. It takes the second output (our incrementing number and the image resolution) and assigns that to &lt;code&gt;$fr&lt;/code&gt;. The variable names are arbitrary; you can call them whatever you want.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run our &lt;code&gt;rename&lt;/code&gt; commands as if we&amp;rsquo;d manually entered them in the terminal one by one, we can use &lt;code&gt;echo $(some command)&lt;/code&gt;. Finally, &lt;code&gt;done&lt;/code&gt; ends our &lt;code&gt;while&lt;/code&gt; loop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bonus-round-rainbow-output&#34;&gt;Bonus round: rainbow output!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wasn&amp;rsquo;t kidding with that &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/tehmaze/lolcat&#34;&gt;&amp;ldquo;rainbow-coloured&amp;rdquo; bit&amp;hellip;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;$ pip install lolcat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s our full code:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;$ file IMG* &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; awk &lt;span class=&#34;s1&#34;&gt;&amp;#39;BEGIN{a=0} {print substr($1, 1, length($1)-5),a++&amp;#34;_&amp;#34;substr($8,1, length($8)-1)}&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;while&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;read&lt;/span&gt; fn fs&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;nb&#34;&gt;echo&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;$(&lt;/span&gt;rename -v &lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;&amp;#34;s/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$fn&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;/img_&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;nv&#34;&gt;$fs&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;s2&#34;&gt;/g&amp;#34;&lt;/span&gt; *&lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;k&#34;&gt;done&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&#34;p&#34;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; lolcat&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><enclosure url="https://victoria.dev/verbose/batch-renaming-images-including-image-resolution-with-awk/renaming-rainbow_hua6bda34c4dd82ff49a9f97483b0665f2_159523_640x0_resize_box_2.png" type="image/jpg"/></item><item><title>How I created custom desktop notifications using terminal and cron</title><link>https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-i-created-custom-desktop-notifications-using-terminal-and-cron/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 10:48:38 +0700</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-i-created-custom-desktop-notifications-using-terminal-and-cron/</guid><description>How you can use tools your Linux system already has to create custom desktop notifications.</description><content:encoded>
&lt;img src="https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-i-created-custom-desktop-notifications-using-terminal-and-cron/dunstnotif_hu2db72365279baf699eed9b7492972369_54170_640x0_resize_box_2.png" width="640" height="320"/>
&lt;p&gt;In my last post I talked about moving from Windows 10 to running i3 on Linux, built up from Debian Base System. Among other things, this change has taught me about the benefits of using basic tools and running a minimal, lightweight system. You can achieve a lot of functionality with just command line tools and simple utilities. One example I&amp;rsquo;d like to illustrate in this post is setting up desktop notifications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I use &lt;a href=&#34;http://knopwob.org/dunst/&#34;&gt;dunst&lt;/a&gt; for desktop notifications. It&amp;rsquo;s a simple, lightweight tool that is easy to configure, doesn&amp;rsquo;t have many dependencies, and can be used across various distributions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;battery-status-low-battery-notification&#34;&gt;Battery status/low battery notification&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was looking for a simple, versatile set up to create notifications for my battery status without having to rely on separate, standalone GUI apps or services. In my search I came across a simple one-line cron task that seemed to be the perfect fit. I adapted it to my purpose and it looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-conf&#34; data-lang=&#34;conf&#34;&gt;# m h dom mon dow command
*/5 * * * * acpi --battery | awk -F, &amp;#39;/Discharging/ { if (int($2) &amp;lt; 20) print }&amp;#39; | xargs -ri env DISPLAY=:0 notify-send -u critical -i &amp;#34;/usr/share/icons/Paper/16x16/status/xfce-battery-critical.png&amp;#34; -t 3000 &amp;#34;{}\nBattery low!&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Psst&amp;hellip; &lt;a href=&#34;https://crontab.guru/&#34;&gt;here&amp;rsquo;s a great tool&lt;/a&gt; for formatting your crontab times.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a lot going on here, so let&amp;rsquo;s break it down:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;*/5 * * * *&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Every five minutes, do the following.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;acpi --battery&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Execute &lt;code&gt;acpi&lt;/code&gt; and show battery information, which on its own returns something akin to:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;Battery 0: Discharging, 65%, 03:01:27 remaining&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pretty straightforward so far. At any point you could input &lt;code&gt;acpi --battery&lt;/code&gt; in a terminal and receive the status output. Today&amp;rsquo;s post, however, is about receiving this information passively in a desktop notification. So, moving on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;| awk -F, &#39;/Discharging/ { if (int($2) &amp;lt; 20) print }&#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Pipe (&lt;code&gt;|&lt;/code&gt;) the result of the previous command to &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt;. (If you don&amp;rsquo;t know what pipe does, here&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://superuser.com/questions/756158/what-does-the-linux-pipe-symbol-do&#34;&gt;an answer from superuser.com&lt;/a&gt; that explains it pretty well, I think.) &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; can do a lot of things, but in this case, we&amp;rsquo;re using it to examine the status of our battery. Let&amp;rsquo;s zoom in on the &lt;code&gt;awk&lt;/code&gt; command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;awk -F, &#39;/Discharging/ { if (int($2) &amp;lt; 20) print }&#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Basically, we&amp;rsquo;re saying, &amp;ldquo;Hey, awk, look at that input you just got and try to find the word &amp;ldquo;discharging,&amp;rdquo; then look to see if the number after the first comma is less than 20. If so, print the whole input.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;| xargs -ri&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Pipe the result of the previous command to &lt;code&gt;xargs&lt;/code&gt;, which takes it as its input and does more stuff with it. &lt;code&gt;-ri&lt;/code&gt; is equivalent to &lt;code&gt;-r&lt;/code&gt; (run the next command only if it receives arguments) and &lt;code&gt;-i&lt;/code&gt; (look for &amp;ldquo;{}&amp;rdquo; and replace it with the input). So in this example, xargs serves as our gatekeeper and messenger for the next command.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;env DISPLAY=:0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Run the following utility in the specified display, in this case, the first display of the local machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;notify-send -u critical -i &amp;quot;/usr/share/icons/Paper/16x16/status/xfce-battery-critical.png&amp;quot; -t 3000 &amp;quot;{}\nLow battery!&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Shows a desktop notification with &lt;code&gt;-u critical&lt;/code&gt; (critical urgency), &lt;code&gt;-i&lt;/code&gt; (the specified icon), &lt;code&gt;-t 3000&lt;/code&gt; (display time/expires after 3000 milliseconds), and finally &lt;code&gt;{}&lt;/code&gt; (the output of awk, replaced by xargs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not bad for a one-liner! I made a few modifications for different states of my battery. Here they all are in my crontab:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre class=&#34;chroma&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-conf&#34; data-lang=&#34;conf&#34;&gt;# m h dom mon dow command
*/5 * * * * acpi --battery | awk -F, &amp;#39;/Discharging/ { if ( (int($2) &amp;lt; 30) &amp;amp;&amp;amp; (int($2) &amp;gt; 15) ) print }&amp;#39; | xargs -ri env DISPLAY=:0 notify-send -a &amp;#34;Battery status&amp;#34; -u normal -i &amp;#34;/usr/share/icons/Paper/16x16/status/xfce-battery-low.png&amp;#34; -t 3000 &amp;#34;{}\nBattery low!&amp;#34;
*/5 * * * * acpi --battery | awk -F, &amp;#39;/Discharging/ { if (int($2) &amp;lt; 15) print }&amp;#39; | xargs -ri env DISPLAY=:0 notify-send -a &amp;#34;Battery status&amp;#34; -u critical -i &amp;#34;/usr/share/icons/Paper/16x16/status/xfce-battery-critical.png&amp;#34; -t 3000 &amp;#34;{}\nSeriously, plug me in.&amp;#34;
*/60 * * * * acpi --battery | awk -F, &amp;#39;/Discharging/ { if (int($2) &amp;gt; 30) print }&amp;#39; | xargs -ri env DISPLAY=:0 notify-send -a &amp;#34;Battery status&amp;#34; -u normal -i &amp;#34;/usr/share/icons/Paper/16x16/status/xfce-battery-ok.png&amp;#34; &amp;#34;{}&amp;#34;
*/60 * * * * acpi --battery | awk -F, &amp;#39;/Charging/ { print }&amp;#39; | xargs -ri env DISPLAY=:0 notify-send -a &amp;#34;Battery status&amp;#34; -u normal -i &amp;#34;/usr/share/icons/Paper/16x16/status/xfce-battery-ok-charging.png&amp;#34; &amp;#34;{}&amp;#34;
*/60 * * * * acpi --battery | awk -F, &amp;#39;/Charging/ { if (int($2) == 100) print }&amp;#39; | xargs -ri env DISPLAY=:0 notify-send -a &amp;#34;Battery status&amp;#34; -u normal -i &amp;#34;/usr/share/icons/Paper/16x16/status/xfce-battery-full-charging.png&amp;#34; &amp;#34;Fully charged.&amp;#34;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the way, you can open your crontab in the editor of your choice by accessing it as root from the &lt;code&gt;/var/spool/cron/crontabs/&lt;/code&gt; directory. It&amp;rsquo;s generally best practice however to make changes to your crontab with the command &lt;code&gt;crontab -e&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see that each notification makes use of the &lt;code&gt;{}&lt;/code&gt; placeholder that tells xargs to put its input there - except for the last one. This is interesting because in this case, we&amp;rsquo;re only using &lt;code&gt;xargs -ri&lt;/code&gt; as a kind of switch to present the notification. The actual information that was the input for xargs is not needed in the output in order to create a notification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;additional-notifications-with-command-line-tools&#34;&gt;Additional notifications with command line tools&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With cron and just a few combinations of simple command line tools, you can create interesting and useful notifications. Consider the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;periodically-check-your-dhcp-address&#34;&gt;Periodically check your dhcp address&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;*/60 * * * * journalctl | awk -F: &#39;/dhcp/ &amp;amp;&amp;amp; /address/ { print $5 }&#39; | tail -1 | xargs -ri env DISPLAY=:0 notify-send -a &amp;quot;dhcp address&amp;quot; -u normal &amp;quot;{}&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which does the following:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;code&gt;*/60 * * * *&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Every 60 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;journalctl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Take the contents of your system log.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;| awk -F: &#39;/dhcp/ &amp;amp;&amp;amp; /address/ { print $5 }&#39;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Find logs containing both &amp;ldquo;dhcp&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;address&amp;rdquo; and output the 5th portion as separated by &amp;ldquo;:&amp;rdquo; (the time field counts).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;| tail -1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Take the last line of the output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;| xargs -ri env DISPLAY=:0 notify-send -a &amp;quot;dhcp address&amp;quot; -u normal &amp;quot;{}&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Create the desktop notification including the output.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;periodically-display-the-time-and-date&#34;&gt;Periodically display the time and date&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;*/60 * * * * timedatectl status | awk -F\n &#39;/Local time/ { print }&#39; | xargs -ri env DISPLAY=:0 notify-send -a &amp;quot;Current Time&amp;quot; -u normal &amp;quot;{}&amp;quot;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;system-log-activity&#34;&gt;System log activity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also search your system logs (try &lt;code&gt;journalctl&lt;/code&gt;) for any number of things using awk, enabling you to get periodic notifications of virtually any logged events.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;experiment&#34;&gt;Experiment!&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As with all things, you are only limited by your imagination! I hope this post has given you some idea about the endless possibilities of these simple utilities. Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded><enclosure url="https://victoria.dev/verbose/how-i-created-custom-desktop-notifications-using-terminal-and-cron/dunstnotif_hu2db72365279baf699eed9b7492972369_54170_640x0_resize_box_2.png" type="image/jpg"/></item></channel></rss>