<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>linux on victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/linux/</link><description>Recent content in linux on victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 01:38:07 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/linux/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Create a self-hosted chat service with your own Matrix server</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/create-a-self-hosted-chat-service-with-your-own-matrix-server/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 01:38:07 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/create-a-self-hosted-chat-service-with-your-own-matrix-server/</guid><description>Matrix is an open standard for decentralized real-time communication. The specification is production-ready and bridges to tons of silo products like Slack, Gitter, Telegram, Discord, and even Facebook Messenger. This lets you use Matrix to link together disjoint communities in one place, or create an alternative communication method that works with, but is independent of, communication silos.
You can create your own self-hosted Matrix chat for as little as $3.50 USD per month on an AWS Lightsail instance.</description></item><item><title>Three rules for choosing a VPN that takes your privacy seriously</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-rules-for-choosing-a-vpn-that-takes-your-privacy-seriously/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 04:41:37 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-rules-for-choosing-a-vpn-that-takes-your-privacy-seriously/</guid><description>Most people know that a VPN is meant to protect your privacy on public or open Wi-Fi. A lesser-known purpose is to protect your privacy right in your own home, from your own internet service provider (ISP).
A set of Federal Communications Commission (FCC) rules entitled &amp;ldquo;Protecting the Privacy of Customers of Broadband and Other Telecommunications Services&amp;rdquo; were unfortunately struck down in 2017. These rules would have prevented ISPs from using and selling your sensitive personal data, such as precise geographic location, health and financial information, web browsing history, and even the content of the messages you send.</description></item><item><title>Deceptively simple search-and-replace across multiple files</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/deceptively-simple-search-and-replace-across-multiple-files/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Aug 2020 04:48:39 -0600</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/deceptively-simple-search-and-replace-across-multiple-files/</guid><description>While a multitude of methods exist to search for and replace words in a single file, what do you do when you&amp;rsquo;ve got a string to update across multiple unrelated files, all with different names? You harness the power of command line tools, of course!
First, you&amp;rsquo;ll need to find all the files you want to change. Stringing together what are effectively search queries for find is really only limited by your imagination.</description></item><item><title>Command line tricks for managing your messy open source repository</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/command-line-tricks-for-managing-your-messy-open-source-repository/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Feb 2020 08:05:06 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/command-line-tricks-for-managing-your-messy-open-source-repository/</guid><description>Effective collaboration, especially in open source software development, starts with effective organization. To make sure that nothing gets missed, the general rule, &amp;ldquo;one issue, one pull request&amp;rdquo; is a nice rule of thumb.
Instead of opening an issue with a large scope like, &amp;ldquo;Fix all the broken links in the documentation,&amp;rdquo; open source projects will have more luck attracting contributors with several smaller and more manageable issues. In the preceding example, you might scope broken links by section or by page.</description></item><item><title>Bash and shell expansions: lazy list-making</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/bash-and-shell-expansions-lazy-list-making/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2019 07:07:24 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/bash-and-shell-expansions-lazy-list-making/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s that time of year again! When stores start putting up colourful sparkly lit-up plastic bits, we all begin to feel a little festive, and by festive I mean let&amp;rsquo;s go shopping. Specifically, holiday gift shopping! (Gifts for yourself are still gifts, technically.)
Just so this doesn&amp;rsquo;t all go completely madcap, you ought to make some gift lists. Bash can help.
Brace expansion These are not braces: ()
Neither are these: []</description></item><item><title>A portable Makefile for continuous delivery with Hugo and GitHub Pages</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-portable-makefile-for-continuous-delivery-with-hugo-and-github-pages/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2019 09:09:06 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-portable-makefile-for-continuous-delivery-with-hugo-and-github-pages/</guid><description>Fun fact: I first launched this GitHub Pages site 1,018 days ago.
Since then, we&amp;rsquo;ve grown together. From early cringe-worthy commit messages, through eighty-six versions of Hugo, and up until last week, a less-than-streamlined multi-app continuous integration and deployment (CI/CD) workflow.
If you know me at all, you know I love to automate things. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using a combination of AWS Lambda, Netlify, and Travis CI to automatically build and publish this site.</description></item><item><title>How to set up OpenVPN on AWS EC2 and fix DNS leaks on Ubuntu 18.04 LTS</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-set-up-openvpn-on-aws-ec2-and-fix-dns-leaks-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 09:01:23 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-set-up-openvpn-on-aws-ec2-and-fix-dns-leaks-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts/</guid><description>Rolling your own Virtual Private Network (VPN) is complicated. I put a lot of time and effort into setting up OpenVPN on my own AWS EC2 instance, yet was still delighted to outsource the ongoing maintenance when I found my preferred privacy-focused VPN.
That said, there&amp;rsquo;s no better way to strive for maximum privacy than a VPN service you control, configure, and maintain yourself. Here&amp;rsquo;s a step-by-step tutorial for setting up your own OpenVPN on AWS EC2, and how to check for and fix DNS leaks.</description></item><item><title>How to do twice as much with half the keystrokes using `.bashrc`</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-do-twice-as-much-with-half-the-keystrokes-using-.bashrc/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2019 09:17:02 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-do-twice-as-much-with-half-the-keystrokes-using-.bashrc/</guid><description>In my recent post about setting up Ubuntu with Bash scripts, I briefly alluded to the magic of .bashrc. This didn&amp;rsquo;t really do it justice, so here&amp;rsquo;s a quick post that offers a bit more detail about what the Bash configuration file can do.
My current configuration hugely improves my workflow, and saves me well over 50% of the keystrokes I would have to employ without it! Let&amp;rsquo;s look at some examples of aliases, functions, and prompt configurations that can improve our workflow by helping us be more efficient with fewer key presses.</description></item><item><title>How to set up a fresh Ubuntu desktop using only dotfiles and bash scripts</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-set-up-a-fresh-ubuntu-desktop-using-only-dotfiles-and-bash-scripts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2019 07:58:18 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-set-up-a-fresh-ubuntu-desktop-using-only-dotfiles-and-bash-scripts/</guid><description>One of my most favorite things about open source files on GitHub is the ability to see how others do (what some people might call) mundane things, like set up their .bashrc and other dotfiles. While I&amp;rsquo;m not as enthusiastic about ricing as I was when I first came to the Linux side, I still get pretty excited when I find a config setting that makes things prettier and faster, and thus, better.</description></item><item><title>How to write Bash one-liners for cloning and managing GitHub and GitLab repositories</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-write-bash-one-liners-for-cloning-and-managing-github-and-gitlab-repositories/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 10:55:19 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-write-bash-one-liners-for-cloning-and-managing-github-and-gitlab-repositories/</guid><description>Few things are more satisfying to me than one elegant line of Bash that automates hours of tedious work. As part of some recent explorations into automatically re-creating my laptop with Bash scripts, I wanted to find a way to easily clone my GitHub-hosted repositories to a new machine. After a bit of digging around, I wrote a one-liner that did just that. Then, in the spirit of not putting all our eggs in the same basket, I wrote another one-liner to automatically create and push to GitLab-hosted backups as well.</description></item><item><title>A quick guide to changing your GitHub username</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-quick-guide-to-changing-your-github-username/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jul 2019 15:19:13 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-quick-guide-to-changing-your-github-username/</guid><description>This being the 2,38947234th and probably last time I&amp;rsquo;ll change my username, (marriage is permanent, right?) I thought I&amp;rsquo;d better write a quick post on how this transition can be achieved as smoothly as possible. You can read official instructions on how to change your GitHub username here, and they will tell you how to do it and what happens. The following is a quick guide to some things to consider afterwards.</description></item><item><title>A remote sync solution for iOS and Linux: Git and Working Copy</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-remote-sync-solution-for-ios-and-linux-git-and-working-copy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2019 11:55:28 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-remote-sync-solution-for-ios-and-linux-git-and-working-copy/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m always looking for pockets of time in which I can be productive. If you add up the minutes you spend in limbo while waiting in line, commuting, or waiting for food delivery (just me?), you may just find an extra hour or two in your day.
To take full advantage of these bits of time, I needed a solution that let me pick up work on my Git repositories wherever I happen to be.</description></item><item><title>Batch renaming images, including image resolution, with awk</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/batch-renaming-images-including-image-resolution-with-awk/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2017 13:59:30 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/batch-renaming-images-including-image-resolution-with-awk/</guid><description>The most recent item on my list of &amp;ldquo;Geeky things I did that made me feel pretty awesome&amp;rdquo; is an hour&amp;rsquo;s adventure that culminated in this code:
$ file IMG* | awk &amp;#39;BEGIN{a=0} {print substr($1, 1, length($1)-5),a++&amp;#34;_&amp;#34;substr($8,1, length($8)-1)}&amp;#39; | while read fn fr; do echo $(rename -v &amp;#34;s/$fn/img_$fr/g&amp;#34; *); done IMG_20170808_172653_425.jpg renamed as img_0_4032x3024.jpg IMG_20170808_173020_267.jpg renamed as img_1_3024x3506.jpg IMG_20170808_173130_616.jpg renamed as img_2_3024x3779.jpg IMG_20170808_173221_425.jpg renamed as img_3_3024x3780.jpg IMG_20170808_173417_059.jpg renamed as img_4_2956x2980.jpg IMG_20170808_173450_971.</description></item><item><title>How I turned Unity into a tiling window manager</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-i-turned-unity-into-a-tiling-window-manager/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 16:10:10 +0800</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-i-turned-unity-into-a-tiling-window-manager/</guid><description>Since Ubuntu 17.10, a default installation of Ubuntu Desktop uses GNOME instead of Unity. After a long and loving battle experience using i3 as my workhorse window manager on my old laptop, I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to mainly use Unity on my new laptop instead. I&amp;rsquo;m a huge fan of tiling window managers as a result of my i3 experience, however, the time it took to configure everything is longer than I wanted to spend getting set up before getting to work with my new laptop.</description></item><item><title>How I set up a single Dropbox folder on my dual-boot Windows and Linux system</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-i-set-up-a-single-dropbox-folder-on-my-dual-boot-windows-and-linux-system/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2017 10:58:01 +0800</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-i-set-up-a-single-dropbox-folder-on-my-dual-boot-windows-and-linux-system/</guid><description>This article is deprecated. For an overview of an updated and truly cross-platform remote sync solution based on Git, please see this article: A remote sync solution for iOS and Linux: Git and Working Copy. June 14, 2018: Ben Newhouse, former head of Sync at Dropbox, was kind enough to inform me that this set up might have unintended ill effects on your Dropbox data:
Dropbox on Windows and Linux maintain metadata on each OS differently, so they&amp;rsquo;ll confuse each other.</description></item><item><title>How I created custom desktop notifications using terminal and cron</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-i-created-custom-desktop-notifications-using-terminal-and-cron/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Feb 2017 10:48:38 +0700</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-i-created-custom-desktop-notifications-using-terminal-and-cron/</guid><description>In my last post I talked about moving from Windows 10 to running i3 on Linux, built up from Debian Base System. Among other things, this change has taught me about the benefits of using basic tools and running a minimal, lightweight system. You can achieve a lot of functionality with just command line tools and simple utilities. One example I&amp;rsquo;d like to illustrate in this post is setting up desktop notifications.</description></item><item><title>How a lifelong Windows user switched to Linux... the hard way</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-a-lifelong-windows-user-switched-to-linux...-the-hard-way/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2017 14:23:59 +0700</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-a-lifelong-windows-user-switched-to-linux...-the-hard-way/</guid><description>Let me preface this by saying that I&amp;rsquo;ve always been interested in finding out how things work. If a thing does something, I want to know why, how, and if I can customize it.
It should come as no surprise that Windows 10 drove me crazy.
Seemingly arbitrary updates that made for a long start-up process on any given day, surprise restarts that meant I&amp;rsquo;d lose my session and thus my thought process from the day before, and the worst part was I never knew what purpose they served.</description></item></channel></rss>