<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>api on victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/api/</link><description>Recent content in api on victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 04:52:50 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/api/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Build your own serverless subscriber list with Go and AWS</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/build-your-own-serverless-subscriber-list-with-go-and-aws/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 04:52:50 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/build-your-own-serverless-subscriber-list-with-go-and-aws/</guid><description>You can now subscribe to my email list on victoria.dev! Here&amp;rsquo;s how I lovingly built a subscription sign up flow with email confirmation that doesn&amp;rsquo;t suck. You can too.
Introducing Simple Subscribe If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in managing your own mailing list or newsletter, you can set up Simple Subscribe on your own AWS resources to collect email addresses. This open source API is written in Go, and runs on AWS Lambda.</description></item><item><title>Look mom, I'm a GitHub Action Hero</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/look-mom-im-a-github-action-hero/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 09:06:33 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/look-mom-im-a-github-action-hero/</guid><description>GitHub recently interviewed me for their blog editorial entitled GitHub Action Hero: Victoria Drake. Here&amp;rsquo;s a behind-the-scenes peek at the original interview questions and my answers.
What is the name of your Action? Please include a link too. Among the several Actions I&amp;rsquo;ve built, I have two current favorites. One is hugo-remote, which lets you continuously deploy a Hugo static site from a private source repository to a public GitHub Pages repository.</description></item><item><title>Publishing GitHub event data with GitHub Actions and Pages</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/publishing-github-event-data-with-github-actions-and-pages/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 09:13:23 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/publishing-github-event-data-with-github-actions-and-pages/</guid><description>Teams who work on GitHub rely on event data to collaborate. The data recorded as issues, pull requests, and comments, become vital to understanding the project.
With the general availability of GitHub Actions, we have a chance to programmatically access and preserve GitHub event data in our repository. Making the data part of the repository itself is a way of preserving it outside of GitHub, and also gives us the ability to feature the data on a front-facing website, such as with GitHub Pages, through an automated process that&amp;rsquo;s part of our CI/CD pipeline.</description></item><item><title>The basics of streaming with Twitter API</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/the-basics-of-streaming-with-twitter-api/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2017 16:39:29 +0700</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/the-basics-of-streaming-with-twitter-api/</guid><description>Twitter has begun asking users to apply to use the API, presumably to cut down on unpalatable uses. This article is still relevant, however, no longer represents the best way to get started with Twitter API streaming. For more on the current API, please see the Twitter API Docs. This post covers my initial adventures in exploring Twitter&amp;rsquo;s Streaming API. I&amp;rsquo;ll talk about:
Getting started making a Twitter Streaming program using a template Problems arising from programming in Python with Windows 10 and Unicode Refining the search function You can follow along with my template on Github.</description></item></channel></rss>