<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>docs on victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/docs/</link><description>Recent content in docs on victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 04:53:10 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/docs/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to write good documentation</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-write-good-documentation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Dec 2020 04:53:10 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-write-good-documentation/</guid><description>If you&amp;rsquo;ve ever half-written a software project before taking a few days off, this is the article you&amp;rsquo;ll discover you needed when you reopen that IDE.
In the technology teams I lead, we make a constant effort to document all the things. Documentation lives alongside the code as an equal player. This helps ensure that no one needs to make assumptions about how something works, or is calling lengthy meetings to gain working knowledge of a feature.</description></item><item><title>Django project best practices to keep your developers happy</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/django-project-best-practices-to-keep-your-developers-happy/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 04:55:19 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/django-project-best-practices-to-keep-your-developers-happy/</guid><description>Do you want your team to enjoy your development workflow? Do you think building software should be fun and existentially fulfilling? If so, this is the post for you!
I&amp;rsquo;ve been developing with Django for years, and I&amp;rsquo;ve never been happier with my Django project set up than I am right now. Here&amp;rsquo;s how I&amp;rsquo;m making a day of developing with Django the most relaxing and enjoyable development experience possible for myself and my engineering team.</description></item><item><title>How to create a self-documenting Makefile</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-create-a-self-documenting-makefile/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 08:55:19 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-create-a-self-documenting-makefile/</guid><description>My new favorite way to completely underuse a Makefile? Creating personalized, per-project repository workflow command aliases that you can check in.
Can a Makefile improve your DevOps and keep developers happy? How awesome would it be if a new developer working on your project didn&amp;rsquo;t start out by copying and pasting commands from your README? What if instead of:
pip3 install pipenv pipenv shell --python 3.8 pipenv install --dev npm install pre-commit install --install-hooks # look up how to install Framework X.</description></item><item><title>The past ten years, or, how to get better at anything</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/the-past-ten-years-or-how-to-get-better-at-anything/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2019 08:27:31 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/the-past-ten-years-or-how-to-get-better-at-anything/</guid><description>If you want to get better at anything:
Solve your own problems, Write about it, Teach others. 1. Searching, a decade ago I was a young graduate with newly-minted freedoms, and I was about to fall in love. I had plenty of imagination, a couple handfuls of tenacity, and no sense of direction at all.
For much of my youth, when I encountered a problem, I just sort of bumped up against it.</description></item><item><title>Word bugs in software documentation and how to fix them</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/word-bugs-in-software-documentation-and-how-to-fix-them/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 09:01:23 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/word-bugs-in-software-documentation-and-how-to-fix-them/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been an editor longer than I&amp;rsquo;ve been a developer, so this topic for me is a real root issue. 🥁 When I see a great project with poorly-written docs, it hits close to /home. Okay, okay, I&amp;rsquo;m done.
I help the Open Web Application Security Project (OWASP) with their Web Security Testing Guide (WSTG). I was recently tasked with writing a style guide and article template that show how to write technical instruction for testing software applications.</description></item></channel></rss>