<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>protocols on victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/protocols/</link><description>Recent content in protocols on victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 01:38:07 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/protocols/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Create a self-hosted chat service with your own Matrix server</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/create-a-self-hosted-chat-service-with-your-own-matrix-server/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 01:38:07 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/create-a-self-hosted-chat-service-with-your-own-matrix-server/</guid><description>Matrix is an open standard for decentralized real-time communication. The specification is production-ready and bridges to tons of silo products like Slack, Gitter, Telegram, Discord, and even Facebook Messenger. This lets you use Matrix to link together disjoint communities in one place, or create an alternative communication method that works with, but is independent of, communication silos.
You can create your own self-hosted Matrix chat for as little as $3.50 USD per month on an AWS Lightsail instance.</description></item><item><title>What is TCP/IP? Layers and protocols explained</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/what-is-tcp/ip-layers-and-protocols-explained/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 04:01:22 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/what-is-tcp/ip-layers-and-protocols-explained/</guid><description>A significant part of the process of creation is the ability to imagine things that do not yet exist. This skill was instrumental to the creation of the Internet. If no one had imagined the underlying technology that most now take for granted every day, there would be no cat memes.
To make the Internet possible, two things that needed imagining are layers and protocols. Layers are conceptual divides that group similar functions together.</description></item><item><title>WPA Key, WPA2, WPA3, and WEP Key: Wi-Fi security explained</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/wpa-key-wpa2-wpa3-and-wep-key-wi-fi-security-explained/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 04:02:27 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/wpa-key-wpa2-wpa3-and-wep-key-wi-fi-security-explained/</guid><description>Setting up new Wi-Fi? Picking the type of password you need can seem like an arbitrary choice. After all, WEP, WPA, WPA2, and WPA3 all have mostly the same letters in them. A password is a password, so what&amp;rsquo;s the difference?
About 60 seconds to billions of years, as it turns out.
All Wi-Fi encryption is not created equal. Let&amp;rsquo;s explore what makes these four acronyms so different, and how you can best protect your home and organization Wi-Fi.</description></item><item><title>What is TLS? Transport Layer Security encryption explained in plain english</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/what-is-tls-transport-layer-security-encryption-explained-in-plain-english/</link><pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 04:48:39 -0600</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/what-is-tls-transport-layer-security-encryption-explained-in-plain-english/</guid><description>If you want to have a confidential conversation with someone you know, you might meet up in person and find a private place to talk. If you want to send data confidentially over the Internet, you might have a few more considerations to cover.
TLS, or Transport Layer Security, refers to a protocol. &amp;ldquo;Protocol&amp;rdquo; is a word that means, &amp;ldquo;the way we&amp;rsquo;ve agreed to do things around here,&amp;rdquo; more or less.</description></item></channel></rss>