<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>data on victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/data/</link><description>Recent content in data on victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 04:00:43 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Digital resilience: redundancy for websites and communications</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/digital-resilience-redundancy-for-websites-and-communications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 04:00:43 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/digital-resilience-redundancy-for-websites-and-communications/</guid><description>When what seems like half the planet noped out of WhatsApp after its terms of service update, applications like Signal (which I highly recommend) saw an unprecedented increase in user traffic. Signal had so many new users sign up that it overwhelmed their existing infrastructure and lead to a 24-hour-ish outage. The small team responded impressively quickly, especially given that a 4,200% spike in new users was utterly implausible before it ocurred.</description></item><item><title>Add search to Hugo static sites with Lunr</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/add-search-to-hugo-static-sites-with-lunr/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 09:25:17 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/add-search-to-hugo-static-sites-with-lunr/</guid><description>Yes, you can have an interactive search feature on your static site! No need for servers or paid subscriptions here. Thanks to the open source Lunr and the power of Hugo static site generator, you can create a client-side search index with just a template and some JavaScript.
A number of my readers have been kind enough to tell me that you find my blog useful, but there&amp;rsquo;s something that you don&amp;rsquo;t know.</description></item><item><title>What is TCP/IP? Layers and protocols explained</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/what-is-tcp/ip-layers-and-protocols-explained/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Nov 2020 04:01:22 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/what-is-tcp/ip-layers-and-protocols-explained/</guid><description>A significant part of the process of creation is the ability to imagine things that do not yet exist. This skill was instrumental to the creation of the Internet. If no one had imagined the underlying technology that most now take for granted every day, there would be no cat memes.
To make the Internet possible, two things that needed imagining are layers and protocols. Layers are conceptual divides that group similar functions together.</description></item><item><title>Build your own serverless subscriber list with Go and AWS</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/build-your-own-serverless-subscriber-list-with-go-and-aws/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 04:52:50 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/build-your-own-serverless-subscriber-list-with-go-and-aws/</guid><description>You can now subscribe to my email list on victoria.dev! Here&amp;rsquo;s how I lovingly built a subscription sign up flow with email confirmation that doesn&amp;rsquo;t suck. You can too.
Introducing Simple Subscribe If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in managing your own mailing list or newsletter, you can set up Simple Subscribe on your own AWS resources to collect email addresses. This open source API is written in Go, and runs on AWS Lambda.</description></item><item><title>Three rules for choosing a VPN that takes your privacy seriously</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-rules-for-choosing-a-vpn-that-takes-your-privacy-seriously/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Oct 2020 04:41:37 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/three-rules-for-choosing-a-vpn-that-takes-your-privacy-seriously/</guid><description>Most people know that a VPN is meant to protect your privacy on public or open Wi-Fi. A lesser-known purpose is to protect your privacy right in your own home, from your own internet service provider (ISP).
A set of Federal Communications Commission (FCC) rules entitled &amp;ldquo;Protecting the Privacy of Customers of Broadband and Other Telecommunications Services&amp;rdquo; were unfortunately struck down in 2017. These rules would have prevented ISPs from using and selling your sensitive personal data, such as precise geographic location, health and financial information, web browsing history, and even the content of the messages you send.</description></item><item><title>Manipulating data with Django migrations</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/manipulating-data-with-django-migrations/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 02:12:57 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/manipulating-data-with-django-migrations/</guid><description>Growing, successful applications are a lovely problem to have. As a product develops, it tends to accumulate complication the way your weekend cake project accumulates layers of frosting. Thankfully, Django, my favorite batteries-included framework, handles complexity pretty well.
Django models help humans work with data in a way that makes sense to our brains, and the framework offers plenty of classes you can inherit to help you rapidly develop a robust application from scratch.</description></item><item><title>Outsourcing security with 1Password, Authy, and Privacy.com</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/outsourcing-security-with-1password-authy-and-privacy.com/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 08:12:32 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/outsourcing-security-with-1password-authy-and-privacy.com/</guid><description>We&amp;rsquo;ve already got enough to deal with without worrying about our cybersecurity. When humans are busy and under stress, we tend to get lax in less-obviously-pressing areas, like the integrity of our online accounts. These areas only become an obvious problem when it&amp;rsquo;s too late for prevention.
Cybersecurity can be fiddly and time-consuming. You might need to reset forgotten passwords, transfer multifactor authentication (MFA) codes to different devices, or deal with the fallout of compromised payment details in the event one of your accounts is still breached.</description></item><item><title>SQLite in production with WAL 🔥</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/sqlite-in-production-with-wal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 10:14:43 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/sqlite-in-production-with-wal/</guid><description>Update: read the HackerNews discussion.
SQLite (&amp;ldquo;see-quell-lite&amp;rdquo;) is a lightweight Sequel, or Structured Query Language (SQL), database engine. Instead of using the client-server database management system model, SQLite is self-contained in a single file. It is library, database, and data, all in one package.
For certain applications, SQLite is a solid choice for a production database. It&amp;rsquo;s lightweight, ultra-portable, and has no external dependencies. Remember when MacBook Air first came out?</description></item><item><title>Multithreaded Python: slithering through an I/O bottleneck</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/multithreaded-python-slithering-through-an-i/o-bottleneck/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2020 09:31:02 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/multithreaded-python-slithering-through-an-i/o-bottleneck/</guid><description>I recently developed a project that I called Hydra: a multithreaded link checker written in Python. Unlike many Python site crawlers I found while researching, Hydra uses only standard libraries, with no external dependencies like BeautifulSoup. It&amp;rsquo;s intended to be run as part of a CI/CD process, so part of its success depended on being fast.
Multiple threads in Python is a bit of a bitey subject (not sorry) in that the Python interpreter doesn&amp;rsquo;t actually let multiple threads execute at the same time.</description></item><item><title>A cron job that could save you from a ransomware attack</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-cron-job-that-could-save-you-from-a-ransomware-attack/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2019 08:27:31 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-cron-job-that-could-save-you-from-a-ransomware-attack/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s 2019, and ransomware has become a thing.
Systems that interact with the public, like companies, educational institutions, and public services, are most susceptible. While delivery methods for ransomware vary from the physical realm to communication via social sites and email, all methods only require one person to make one mistake in order for ransomware to proliferate.
Ransomware, as you may have heard, is a malicious program that encrypts your files, rendering them unreadable and useless to you.</description></item><item><title>Publishing GitHub event data with GitHub Actions and Pages</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/publishing-github-event-data-with-github-actions-and-pages/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2019 09:13:23 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/publishing-github-event-data-with-github-actions-and-pages/</guid><description>Teams who work on GitHub rely on event data to collaborate. The data recorded as issues, pull requests, and comments, become vital to understanding the project.
With the general availability of GitHub Actions, we have a chance to programmatically access and preserve GitHub event data in our repository. Making the data part of the repository itself is a way of preserving it outside of GitHub, and also gives us the ability to feature the data on a front-facing website, such as with GitHub Pages, through an automated process that&amp;rsquo;s part of our CI/CD pipeline.</description></item><item><title>Secure application architecture basics: separation, configuration, and access</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/secure-application-architecture-basics-separation-configuration-and-access/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Sep 2019 08:03:12 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/secure-application-architecture-basics-separation-configuration-and-access/</guid><description>Software developers today are encouraged to focus on building, and that&amp;rsquo;s a great thing. We&amp;rsquo;re benefitting from maker culture, an attitude of &amp;ldquo;always be shipping,&amp;rdquo; open source collaboration, and a bevy of apps that help us prioritize and execute with maximum efficiency. We&amp;rsquo;re in an environment of constant creation, where both teams and solo entrepreneurs can be maximally productive.
Sometimes, this breakneck-speed productivity shows its downsides.
As I learn more about security best practices, I can&amp;rsquo;t help but see more and more applications that just don&amp;rsquo;t have a clue.</description></item><item><title>Migrating to the cloud but without screwing it up, or how to move house</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/migrating-to-the-cloud-but-without-screwing-it-up-or-how-to-move-house/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2019 08:03:12 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/migrating-to-the-cloud-but-without-screwing-it-up-or-how-to-move-house/</guid><description>For an application that&amp;rsquo;s ready to scale, not using managed cloud architecture these days is like insisting on digging your own well for water. It&amp;rsquo;s far more labour-intensive, requires buying all your own equipment, takes a lot more time, and there&amp;rsquo;s a higher chance you&amp;rsquo;re going to get it wrong because you don&amp;rsquo;t personally have a whole lot of experience digging wells, anyway.
That said - let&amp;rsquo;s just get this out of the way first - there is no cloud.</description></item><item><title>Hackers are Googling your plain text passwords: preventing sensitive data exposure</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/hackers-are-googling-your-plain-text-passwords-preventing-sensitive-data-exposure/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 09:10:11 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/hackers-are-googling-your-plain-text-passwords-preventing-sensitive-data-exposure/</guid><description>Last week, I wrote about the importance of properly handling user input in our websites and applications. I alluded to an overarching security lesson that I hope to make explicit today: the security of our software, application, and customer data is built from the ground up, long before the product goes live.
The OWASP Top 10 is a comprehensive guide to web application security risks. It is relied upon by technology professionals, corporations, and those interested in cybersecurity or information security.</description></item><item><title>SQL injection and XSS: what white hat hackers know about trusting user input</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/sql-injection-and-xss-what-white-hat-hackers-know-about-trusting-user-input/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 09:01:23 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/sql-injection-and-xss-what-white-hat-hackers-know-about-trusting-user-input/</guid><description>Software developers have a lot on their minds. There are are myriad of questions to ask when it comes to creating a website or application: What technologies will we use? How will the architecture be set up? What functions do we need? What will the UI look like? Especially in a software market where shipping new apps seems more like a race for reputation than a well-considered process, one of the most important questions often falls to the bottom of the &amp;ldquo;Urgent&amp;rdquo; column: how will our product be secured?</description></item><item><title>How to write Bash one-liners for cloning and managing GitHub and GitLab repositories</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-write-bash-one-liners-for-cloning-and-managing-github-and-gitlab-repositories/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2019 10:55:19 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-write-bash-one-liners-for-cloning-and-managing-github-and-gitlab-repositories/</guid><description>Few things are more satisfying to me than one elegant line of Bash that automates hours of tedious work. As part of some recent explorations into automatically re-creating my laptop with Bash scripts, I wanted to find a way to easily clone my GitHub-hosted repositories to a new machine. After a bit of digging around, I wrote a one-liner that did just that. Then, in the spirit of not putting all our eggs in the same basket, I wrote another one-liner to automatically create and push to GitLab-hosted backups as well.</description></item><item><title>Knapsack problem algorithms for my real-life carry-on knapsack</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/knapsack-problem-algorithms-for-my-real-life-carry-on-knapsack/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2018 21:00:35 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/knapsack-problem-algorithms-for-my-real-life-carry-on-knapsack/</guid><description>The knapsack problem I&amp;rsquo;m a nomad and live out of one carry-on bag. This means that the total weight of all my worldly possessions must fall under airline cabin baggage weight limits - usually 10kg. On some smaller airlines, however, this weight limit drops to 7kg. Occasionally, I have to decide not to bring something with me to adjust to the smaller weight limit.
As a practical exercise, deciding what to leave behind (or get rid of altogether) entails laying out all my things and choosing which ones to keep.</description></item><item><title>Things you need to know about becoming a Data Scientist</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/things-you-need-to-know-about-becoming-a-data-scientist/</link><pubDate>Fri, 31 Mar 2017 13:19:19 +0900</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/things-you-need-to-know-about-becoming-a-data-scientist/</guid><description>I recently attended a panel discussion hosted by General Assembly in Singapore entitled, &amp;ldquo;So you want to be a Data Scientist/Analyst&amp;rdquo;. The panel featured professionals in different stages of their careers and offered a wealth of information to an audience of hopefuls, including tips on how to land a job as a data scientist, and stories debunking myths that color this field.
The panelists Misrab Faizullah-Khan - VP of Data Science, GO_JEK Anthony Ta - Data Scientist, Tech in Asia Leow Guo Jun - Data Scientist, GO_JEK Gabriel Jiang - Data Scientist Adam Drake - Chief Data Officer, Atazzo Here&amp;rsquo;s a rundown of the major points discussed, paraphrased for brevity.</description></item></channel></rss>