<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>javascript on victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/javascript/</link><description>Recent content in javascript on victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 09:25:17 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/javascript/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Add search to Hugo static sites with Lunr</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/add-search-to-hugo-static-sites-with-lunr/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 09:25:17 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/add-search-to-hugo-static-sites-with-lunr/</guid><description>Yes, you can have an interactive search feature on your static site! No need for servers or paid subscriptions here. Thanks to the open source Lunr and the power of Hugo static site generator, you can create a client-side search index with just a template and some JavaScript.
A number of my readers have been kind enough to tell me that you find my blog useful, but there&amp;rsquo;s something that you don&amp;rsquo;t know.</description></item><item><title>Adorable bookmarklets want to help delete your social media data</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/adorable-bookmarklets-want-to-help-delete-your-social-media-data/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Jun 2018 13:12:02 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/adorable-bookmarklets-want-to-help-delete-your-social-media-data/</guid><description>A little while ago I wrote about a Lambda function I called ephemeral for deleting my old tweets. While it&amp;rsquo;s a great project for someone familiar with or wanting to learn to use Lambda, it isn&amp;rsquo;t simple for a non-technical person to set up. There are services out there that will delete your tweets for you, but require your access credentials. There didn&amp;rsquo;t seem to be anything that provided convenience without also requiring authentication.</description></item><item><title>A Unicode substitution cipher algorithm</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-unicode-substitution-cipher-algorithm/</link><pubDate>Sat, 06 Jan 2018 20:00:28 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-unicode-substitution-cipher-algorithm/</guid><description>Full transparency: I occasionally waste time messing around on Twitter. (Gasp! Shock!) One of the ways I waste time messing around on Twitter is by writing my name in my profile with different Unicode character &amp;ldquo;fonts,&amp;rdquo; 𝖑𝖎𝖐𝖊 𝖙𝖍𝖎𝖘 𝖔𝖓𝖊. I previously did this by searching for different Unicode characters on Google, then one-by-one copying and pasting them into the &amp;ldquo;Name&amp;rdquo; field on my Twitter profile. Since this method of wasting time was a bit of a time waster, I decided (in true programmer fashion) to write a tool that would help me save some time while wasting it.</description></item><item><title>How to code a satellite algorithm and cook paella from scratch</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-code-a-satellite-algorithm-and-cook-paella-from-scratch/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Sep 2017 16:50:24 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-code-a-satellite-algorithm-and-cook-paella-from-scratch/</guid><description>What if I told you that by the end of this article, you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to calculate the orbital period of satellites around Earth using their average altitudes and&amp;hellip; You tuned out already, didn&amp;rsquo;t you?
Okay, how about this: I&amp;rsquo;m going to teach you how to make paella!
And you&amp;rsquo;ll have written a function that does the stuff I mentioned above, just like I did for a freeCodeCamp challenge.
I promise there&amp;rsquo;s an overarching moral lesson that will benefit you every day for the rest of your life.</description></item><item><title>Making sandwiches with closures in JavaScript</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/making-sandwiches-with-closures-in-javascript/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 09:16:35 +0700</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/making-sandwiches-with-closures-in-javascript/</guid><description>Say you&amp;rsquo;re having a little coding get-together, and you need some sandwiches. You happen to know that everyone prefers a different type of sandwich, like chicken, ham, or peanut butter and mayo. You could make all these sandwiches yourself, but that would be tedious and boring.
Luckily, you know of a nearby sandwich shop that delivers. They have the ability and ingredients to make any kind of sandwich in the world, and all you have to do is order through their app.</description></item><item><title>Understanding Array.prototype.reduce() and recursion using apple pie</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/understanding-array.prototype.reduce-and-recursion-using-apple-pie/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 11:40:06 +0700</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/understanding-array.prototype.reduce-and-recursion-using-apple-pie/</guid><description>I was having trouble understanding reduce() and recursion in JavaScript, so I wrote this article to explain it to myself (hey, look, recursion!). I hope you find my examples both helpful and delicious.
Given an array with nested arrays:
var arr = [1, [2], [3, [[4]]]] We want to produce this:
var flat = [1, 2, 3, 4] Using for loops and if statements Naively, if we know the maximum number of nested arrays we&amp;rsquo;ll encounter (there are 4 in this example), we can use for loops to iterate through each array item, then if statements to check if each item is in itself an array, and so on&amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Iterating over objects and arrays: frequent errors</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/iterating-over-objects-and-arrays-frequent-errors/</link><pubDate>Tue, 16 May 2017 10:46:46 +0700</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/iterating-over-objects-and-arrays-frequent-errors/</guid><description>Here&amp;rsquo;s some complaining a quick overview of some code that has confounded me more than once. I&amp;rsquo;m told even very experienced developers encounter these situations regularly, so if you find yourself on your third cup of coffee scratching your head over why your code is doing exactly what you told it to do (and not what you want it to do), maybe this post can help you.
The example code is JavaScript, since that&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve been working in lately, but I believe the concepts to be pretty universal.</description></item></channel></rss>