<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>aws on victoria.dev</title><link>https://victoria.dev/tags/aws/</link><description>Recent content in aws on victoria.dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><managingEditor>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</managingEditor><webMaster>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</webMaster><lastBuildDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 01:38:07 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://victoria.dev/tags/aws/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Create a self-hosted chat service with your own Matrix server</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/create-a-self-hosted-chat-service-with-your-own-matrix-server/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 01:38:07 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/create-a-self-hosted-chat-service-with-your-own-matrix-server/</guid><description>Matrix is an open standard for decentralized real-time communication. The specification is production-ready and bridges to tons of silo products like Slack, Gitter, Telegram, Discord, and even Facebook Messenger. This lets you use Matrix to link together disjoint communities in one place, or create an alternative communication method that works with, but is independent of, communication silos.
You can create your own self-hosted Matrix chat for as little as $3.50 USD per month on an AWS Lightsail instance.</description></item><item><title>Build your own serverless subscriber list with Go and AWS</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/build-your-own-serverless-subscriber-list-with-go-and-aws/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Nov 2020 04:52:50 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/build-your-own-serverless-subscriber-list-with-go-and-aws/</guid><description>You can now subscribe to my email list on victoria.dev! Here&amp;rsquo;s how I lovingly built a subscription sign up flow with email confirmation that doesn&amp;rsquo;t suck. You can too.
Introducing Simple Subscribe If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in managing your own mailing list or newsletter, you can set up Simple Subscribe on your own AWS resources to collect email addresses. This open source API is written in Go, and runs on AWS Lambda.</description></item><item><title>A cron job that could save you from a ransomware attack</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-cron-job-that-could-save-you-from-a-ransomware-attack/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2019 08:27:31 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/a-cron-job-that-could-save-you-from-a-ransomware-attack/</guid><description>It&amp;rsquo;s 2019, and ransomware has become a thing.
Systems that interact with the public, like companies, educational institutions, and public services, are most susceptible. While delivery methods for ransomware vary from the physical realm to communication via social sites and email, all methods only require one person to make one mistake in order for ransomware to proliferate.
Ransomware, as you may have heard, is a malicious program that encrypts your files, rendering them unreadable and useless to you.</description></item><item><title>Migrating to the cloud but without screwing it up, or how to move house</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/migrating-to-the-cloud-but-without-screwing-it-up-or-how-to-move-house/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2019 08:03:12 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/migrating-to-the-cloud-but-without-screwing-it-up-or-how-to-move-house/</guid><description>For an application that&amp;rsquo;s ready to scale, not using managed cloud architecture these days is like insisting on digging your own well for water. It&amp;rsquo;s far more labour-intensive, requires buying all your own equipment, takes a lot more time, and there&amp;rsquo;s a higher chance you&amp;rsquo;re going to get it wrong because you don&amp;rsquo;t personally have a whole lot of experience digging wells, anyway.
That said - let&amp;rsquo;s just get this out of the way first - there is no cloud.</description></item><item><title>How to set up OpenVPN on AWS EC2 and fix DNS leaks on Ubuntu 18.04 LTS</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-set-up-openvpn-on-aws-ec2-and-fix-dns-leaks-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 09:01:23 -0400</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/how-to-set-up-openvpn-on-aws-ec2-and-fix-dns-leaks-on-ubuntu-18.04-lts/</guid><description>Rolling your own Virtual Private Network (VPN) is complicated. I put a lot of time and effort into setting up OpenVPN on my own AWS EC2 instance, yet was still delighted to outsource the ongoing maintenance when I found my preferred privacy-focused VPN.
That said, there&amp;rsquo;s no better way to strive for maximum privacy than a VPN service you control, configure, and maintain yourself. Here&amp;rsquo;s a step-by-step tutorial for setting up your own OpenVPN on AWS EC2, and how to check for and fix DNS leaks.</description></item><item><title>Why I'm automatically deleting my old tweets using AWS Lambda</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/why-im-automatically-deleting-my-old-tweets-using-aws-lambda/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Apr 2018 10:51:15 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/why-im-automatically-deleting-my-old-tweets-using-aws-lambda/</guid><description>From now on, my tweets are ephemeral. Here’s why I’m deleting all my old tweets, and the AWS Lambda function I’m using to do all this for free.
Click here to skip to the code part.
Stuff and opinions I&amp;rsquo;ve only been a one-bag nomad for a little over a year and a half. Before that, I lived as most people do in an apartment or a house. I owned furniture, more clothing than I strictly needed, and enough &amp;ldquo;stuff&amp;rdquo; to fill at least a few moving boxes.</description></item><item><title>Running a free Twitter bot on AWS Lambda</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/running-a-free-twitter-bot-on-aws-lambda/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Mar 2018 10:29:15 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/running-a-free-twitter-bot-on-aws-lambda/</guid><description>If you read About time, you&amp;rsquo;ll know that I&amp;rsquo;m a big believer in spending time now on building things that save time in the future. To this end I built a simple Twitter bot in Go that would occasionally post links to my articles and keep my account interesting even when I&amp;rsquo;m too busy to use it. The tweets help drive traffic to my sites, and I don&amp;rsquo;t have to lift a finger.</description></item><item><title>Moving to a new domain without breaking old links with AWS &amp; Disqus</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/moving-to-a-new-domain-without-breaking-old-links-with-aws-disqus/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 08:56:20 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/moving-to-a-new-domain-without-breaking-old-links-with-aws-disqus/</guid><description>I started blogging about my nomadic travels last year, and so far the habit has stuck. Like all side projects, I won&amp;rsquo;t typically invest heavily in setting up web properties before I can be reasonably certain that such an investment is worth my time or enjoyment. In other words: don&amp;rsquo;t buy the domain until you&amp;rsquo;ve proven to yourself that you&amp;rsquo;ll stick with it!
After some months of regular posting I felt I was ready to commit (short courtship, I know, but we&amp;rsquo;re all adults here) and I bought a dedicated domain, herOneBag.</description></item><item><title>Hosting your static site with AWS S3, Route 53, and CloudFront</title><link>https://victoria.dev/blog/hosting-your-static-site-with-aws-s3-route-53-and-cloudfront/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 20:46:12 -0500</pubDate><author>hello@victoria.dev (Victoria Drake)</author><guid>https://victoria.dev/blog/hosting-your-static-site-with-aws-s3-route-53-and-cloudfront/</guid><description>Some time ago I decided to stop freeloading on GitHub pages and move one of my sites to Amazon Web Services (AWS). It turns out that I&amp;rsquo;m still mostly freeloading (yay free tier) so it amounted to a learning experience. Here are the components that let me host and serve the site at my custom domain with HTTPS.
Static site in Amazon Web Services S3 bucket Route 53 handling the DNS CloudFront for distribution and a custom SSL certificate I set all that up most of a year ago.</description></item></channel></rss>